<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Man's chief end to glorifie God, or, Some brief sermon notes on I Cor. 10:31 by the reverend Mr. John Bailey.</title>
            <author>Bailey, John, 1644-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B17422</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10789227</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204795</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264170261</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B448</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10789227</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B17422)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1415:1a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Man's chief end to glorifie God, or, Some brief sermon notes on I Cor. 10:31 by the reverend Mr. John Bailey.</title>
                  <author>Bailey, John, 1644-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 160, 40, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Green and are to be sold by Richard Wilkins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To my loving and dearly beloved Christian friends..." appears on its own at reel 2301:13, and is identified as Wing B449.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: Pages faded, stained, tightly bound and torn with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Harvard University Library and the Congregational Library..</note>
                  <note>With: (at reel 1415:1) To my loving and dearly beloved Christian friends, in and about Lymerick. [Boston? : s.n., 1684?]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, X, 31 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204795:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204795:1"/>
            <p>Man's chief <hi>End To Glorifie GOD,</hi> OR <hi>Some Brief SERMON-NOTES On</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the</hi> Reverend Mr. <hi>Iohn Bailey,</hi> Sometime Preacher and Prisoner of <hi>Christ</hi> at <hi>Limerick</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> And now Pastor to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in <hi>Watertown</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 17.4, 5.</hi>
               </bibl> I have Glorified thee on Earth, and now Father Glorifie me with thine own Self.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Pet. 1.15.</hi>
               </bibl> I will endeavour that after my Decease you may have these things al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wayes in remembrance.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Boston</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Green,</hi> and ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be Sold by <hi>Richard Wilkins</hi> Book-Seller near the <hi>Town-House. Anno.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:204795:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204795:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Reverend and Worthy Preacher of the Ensuing Sermons desires none of my Commendation, the most precious and seasonable Subiec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> needs it not, the manner of Handling it has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready had the best Letters Commendatory, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Consciences, Hearts, and Lives of some of them who first sate under the dropping of these Heavenly Showers that fell upon them in <hi>Ireland</hi> where they were Preacht. And altho' they could not but forget many of the words, yet retaining the savour of those Truths then suckt in from his Mouth, they importunately desired that not only <hi>themselves</hi> might have <hi>their minds stirred up by way of Remembrance,</hi> but also that <hi>theirs</hi> and <hi>others</hi> their Fellow-Travellers in the same way, by the same Rule, and unto the same end, might share in the Benefit of this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakening and Affecting Discourse. To gratifie whose Importunity, The almost inexorable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor did in the end (and indeed not till a great fit of sickness had brought him in all appearance near his end) consent to be passive in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of the same.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204795:3"/>
            <p>And purely passive he was therein, utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing (whether out of modesty, melancholy or Bodily Infirmity I say not) to be any otherwise concerned than barely to allow of their Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>The Notes were taken by one who was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faithful and ready Scribe, yet (because written in Long-hand) many things must needs be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and others not so distinctly penned. Had they been taken by a quicker Pen, and perused by <hi>himself,</hi> it might well have been expected they would have been more polished and better drest than they now appear.</p>
            <p>Perhaps they will not <hi>so</hi> please a curious and critical Age wherein men are more for <hi>words</hi> than <hi>things,</hi> for <hi>fine Language</hi> than <hi>substantial Truths,</hi> for <hi>pleasing their Fancy,</hi> than <hi>feeding their Hearts</hi> in order to <hi>mending their Lives,</hi> a sort of Preaching that <hi>Paul</hi> carefully avoided, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. and 2.1. and rather chose to use <hi>great plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Speech,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12. whom our Author has also imitated, as considering that those are the best Sermons that do the most <hi>good,</hi> &amp; those do the most <hi>good</hi> that are most <hi>understood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, serious Souls will relish serious Truths. The foolishness of Preaching <hi>is Gods way</hi> to save Souls, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. and the <hi>wisdom of God</hi> tho' not dispensed in the words of <hi>mans wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> shall be the <hi>power of God to Salvation,</hi> Rom. 1.16. <hi>and Wisdom is and will be justified of her Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204795:3"/>
            <p>I am well assured that our Errand into this world and Business here is to glorify God; and am as fully satisfied that those who mind their Errand and are ingaged in the pursuit of their Business, will be thankful for any help they meet with in the way.</p>
            <p>To have the whole heart and Soul <hi>bent</hi> and set for glorifying of God <hi>here</hi> will be found one of the most infallible Characters of a man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Glory with God <hi>hereafter.</hi> When many whose parts and Gifts both natural and acquired have made a considerable figure in the world, and rendred them observable among Christians, shall be rejected by Christ as seekers of themselves, and workers of Iniquity; then shall those honest, upright Souls who tho' mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in a lower sphear have aimed at this most high and glorious end, be accepted of him who demands the Heart, and values every man by his Heart.</p>
            <p>The answer to that great Inquiry, Whom have we truly and heartily been for? and whose glory have we sought? will over a little while determine the Question concerning the Eternal Estate of all Mankind. God will abate us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this, <hi>Thou shalt be for me and no other, Hos.</hi> 3.3 Nor can any thing be more equal than that he from whom all things are, should have all things to be for him, and all honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rendred to him. While those Jews sought Glory to themselves one of another and not
<pb facs="tcp:204795:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:204795:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:204795:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204795:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:204795:6"/> the Honour that came from God only; our Lord Jesus Christ declares their <hi>coming</hi> to him impossible, <hi>John</hi> 5.44. And by like reason who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever pretends to be a Believer, and yet has not learnt to deny his own vain glory, &amp; to give all the honour that arises from ought done by him unto God only, will thereby discover and evince himself to be a meer pretender. Gods Holiness is that whereby he seeks himself, or his own glory as the ultimate end of all that he does; and hence all that are partakers of his Holiness (as all his Children are) must necessarily (though most voluntarily) do the same.</p>
            <p>It is a solemn caution given by that blessed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle, 2 John 8. <hi>Look to your selves that we lose not what we have wrought, but that we Receive a full Reward.</hi> What God has we shall not lose, and what we do for his Glory he has, and we shall have a good account of in the day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence. How many great contrivances, cost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Actions, splendid performances, which were materially good, and rendred the Agents famous in the world, shall yet miss of acceptance with God, and be eternally lost to the Doers, because in the doing of them they only sought <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,</hi> and not Gods Glory! See 1 Cor. 13.1, 2, 3. The Arrow may be drawn to the Head, but if not well level'd shall never hit the <hi>Mark.</hi> All such Labour will prove Labour in vain.</p>
            <p>Since man by Sin lost his true end, he makes himself his end, and can do no other till he has a
<pb facs="tcp:204795:6"/>
               <hi>new Nature</hi> infused from above, which disposes him to higher Things. No Hypocrite can ever get one Hairs-breadth beyond himself; <hi>Self</hi> is the Principle he acteth from &amp; the End he moveth towards. The new Creature being Gods Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship, and Created after his own Image, is only capable of acting <hi>like his Maker,</hi> and <hi>for his Maker.</hi> The <hi>New-heart</hi> alone can love <hi>this</hi> Text, and practically close with <hi>this</hi> Doctrine. And therefore it behoves every Reader that would be a Doer, and not a Self-deceiver, to be a restless Inquirer for that Heart which the Lord can give, and right Inquirers shall receive, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26, 37.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This farther I have to advertise the Reader of, viz. That there is a Valedictory Epistle annexed, which was penned by the same Author, and left as his last Legacy to that People among whom he had spent so many Laborious Years, and for the everlasting Weal of whom he had such vehement Desires. I must own that I had not the opportunity of perusing it before it was gone to the Press, yet coming from one who understands what he speaks, and lives what he writes, I doubt not of its usefulness to the end propounded,</hi> viz. <hi>nextly the Edification, Consolation and Establishment of those to whom it was directed, and ultimately the Glory of God, and therefore is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry properly joined to such a Treatise that handles</hi> that <hi>Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I commend both the one and the other firstly to those who were nextly concerned in the Studying and
<pb facs="tcp:204795:7"/> now in the publishing thereof; then to all others into whose Hands Divine Providence shall cast this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory. Let it be Read, Studied, Lived. And that such little Books may not be among the Witnesses for the Lord and against any of us in the Great Day of Judgment, is the Hearty Prayer of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204795:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 10.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Whether therefore ye Eat or Drink, or whatsoever ye do, do all to the glory of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Shall not stand upon the Coherence of the Words; only some hints to let you see how the Text comes in.</p>
            <p>I have formerly upon another Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion observed divers things concerning this great Apostle, and this famous Church he here writes unto; and so need not say any thing more here.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:204795:8"/>
            <p>The Text is an Exhortation to all Christians to the end of the World.</p>
            <p>After the Apostle had Treated of many things, as in the beginning of the Chapter, <hi>That the</hi> Israelites <hi>were Baptized unto</hi> Moses <hi>in the Cloud, and in the Sea, and that though they did eat the same spiritual meat, and drink the same spiritual drink, yet they were heavily plagued for their sins,</hi> which especially were <hi>Idolatry, Fornication, Tempting of Christ,</hi> and <hi>Murmuring against God.</hi> And then the Apostle makes use of it to caution us that we do not so, and tells us <hi>tbey are our Examples,</hi> and that these things are written for our <hi>Admonition:</hi> and in <hi>ver.</hi> 13. help is promised under temptation; then he hints at the Lords Supper, exhorting them <hi>to flee from Idolatry,</hi> because that at that Ordinance they have communion with the Body and Blood of Christ, and by Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry they should have communion with Devils, which would be very provoking to God.</p>
            <p>And having desired them to take heed of giving offence to others, especially in Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Drinking, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. he tells them <hi>they may lawfully eat and drink what is set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204795:8"/> them, and sold in the Shambles, ver.</hi> 26, 27. <hi>asking no question for Conscience sake;</hi> but if any should say it were offered to an Idol, then not to give offence by eating, and gives the same reasons both for eating, and not eating, to wit, <hi>ver.</hi> 26.28. <hi>The earth is the Lords and the fulness thereof:</hi> q. d. Though such meat be abused by Idolaters yet it ceas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to be Gods creature, who made it to be eaten with Thanksgiving: and yet if notice were given that it were offered to an Idol, not to eat it, for fear of giving offence, <hi>for the earth is the Lords and the fulness there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,</hi> ver. 28 there are more meats created of God, and you need not eat with offence. And then comes in the Text, they are Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted <hi>to mind the Glory of God</hi> whether they eat or no.</p>
            <p>In the Text you have a precious and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Duty exhorted unto, <hi>To glorify God:</hi> and this is laid down both in general in <hi>whatsoever we do,</hi> and in particular, in <hi>our Eating and Drinking:</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s if those natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Actions were steps in our way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and so not to be despised, or l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st by us.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:204795:9"/>
            <p>
               <label>DOCTRINE.</label>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">It is the grand Duty, and it ought to be the daily desire, and design of every gracious Soul to glorifie God in all it doth, yea even in its very Eating and Drinking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the grand, main duty that runs, or should run through every duty: and it should be our desire, and design, and that daily, and that both in general and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar actions. And if this be not your design in all you do, God hates your performances as he does your iniquities, <hi>Isai.</hi> 1.13, 14. That man was never Regenerated that does not every day (or ordinarily) set out for God. And you ought not only to design Gods glory in general but in particular Actions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Three things are to be attended here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To show what it is in general to glorifie God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What it is to glorifie God in particular
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204795:9"/> and especially in eating &amp; Drinking, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation which may be added to it; though in this <hi>I</hi> shall be very brief, it has been so well handled by others.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Why this should be our design in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing: but this shall come under the Use of Exhortation, and the Motives may serve for Reasons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What is it in general to Glorifie God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> 1. Negatively, it is not to make him better, greater or more glorious, for what can be added to Infiniteness? his essential glory was, is, and will be still the same; its impossible to add to that, but his declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive glory in the World is here meant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Positively it lies in three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In giving him the glory of his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Perfections, by getting and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful maintaining such Notions and Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions of him, in the secret of our Souls as do beget suitable dispositions towards him, and Impressions before him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It consists in this, when the glory of God is plainly to be seen upon the outward face of our Acknowledgment and Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or (take it in these words) Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shiping
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204795:10"/> and Walking.)</p>
            <p n="3">3. It lies in an actual Proposing of the Glory of God, as our outmost end in all our particular actions.</p>
            <p>Now to speak to each of these distinctly:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It lies in giving God the Glory of his wonderful Perfections, by a getting and chearful maintaining such Notions and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions of him, in the secret of our soul; as do beget suitable Affections to him, and Impressions before him.</p>
            <p>Gods Glory is seen in his Perfections, in his wonderful Holiness, Goodness, Wisdom, Faithfulness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that a person is said to glorifie God when he has a right know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of his Perfections; and this knowledg is right when it puts a man upon magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, exalting, &amp; extolling God above every person and thing. The Saints are often said in Scripture to magnifie God, and to call on one another to do so, <hi>Psal.</hi> 34.3, 4. <hi>Luk</hi> 1.46. the word <hi>Magnifie,</hi> signifies <hi>to make great</hi> but this (as you heard before) we can't pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly do: our Righteousness adds nothing to him, <hi>Job</hi> 35.7, 8. it's only a declaring him
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204795:10"/> great (who was infinitely so from Eternity) in our apprehension affections Impressions and Conversations. Hence God is said to magnifie himself when he makes himself known, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38. <hi>ult.</hi> and often said to <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his mercy, and his great Name</hi> when he shows mercy, and works for his Name sake.</p>
            <p>Indeed when God magnifies man (as he is said to do, <hi>Job</hi> 7.17.) He then really adds to him, and makes him greater. God magnified man by Creation, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him a rational Soul, capable of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with himself; he has magnified him much more by Redemption and Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. He is said to Glorifie them <hi>whom he calls,</hi> by putting a <hi>beauty and splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor upon them,</hi> who before were little and unworthy, and he does it both by giving them Grace here, and by raising them to Glory hereafter. Thus God magnifies man and makes him great.</p>
            <p>But we magnifie God when we set up an high Throne for him in our hearts, and make room for him in our Souls: when we do most highly, gloriously and honourably
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204795:11"/> conceive of God, this is a giving Glory to him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.16. with many such like Texts that may fall in our way afterwards. He is glorious in himself, but we make him so to us, when we rightly conceive of him, and are suitably affected towards him.</p>
            <p>In Scripture Gods Glory is said to be his Excellency, and that is above all other things <hi>Isai.</hi> 35.2. <hi>the Glory of the Lord, and the [Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celloncy] of our God.</hi> When we daily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of God as the most Excellent one, this is a <hi>Glorifying God as God. Herod</hi> was destroyed for not giving God the Glory, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.23. how can you Glorifie God when you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get him all the day? this cannot be: we are then Christians to purpose when we Glorifie God as God, preferring him above all, see <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. O how many are guilty of the sins of the <hi>Heathen!</hi> they do not Glorifie God as God; else they could never do that in Gods sight, which they would not do in the sight of a holy Minister, nay not in the sight of a Child.</p>
            <p>Now our notions of God will appear to be right when they beget suitable Dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons toward him, and Impressions before him.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:204795:11"/>1. Suitable Dispositions toward him, and they are five.</p>
            <p n="1">1. These Notions put persons upon ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving of him daily, such do not ordinarily forget God, but every thing puts them in mind of him; and they that would Glorifie God must begin every day, and every duty with a design so to do. Hence sayes <hi>David, My eyes are ever towards the Lord,</hi> Psal. 25.15. the Saints observe God, and God ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves them, <hi>Hos.</hi> 148. <hi>I have seen him, and [Observed] him, and they that are wise and willing will observe these things,</hi> Psal. 107. <hi>ult.</hi> the whole Creation puts a good Soul in mind of God; its Gods Library, you may read your fill, it was the first Bible that ever God wrote: gracious Souls see God in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that he has made, and his glorious perfections in all, and give him the glory of them both in the work of <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence:</hi> as</p>
            <p n="1">1. His wonderful Power in making and upholding all things in their being, beauty, and order, and</p>
            <p n="2">2. His wonderful Wisdom that preserves this World, notwithstanding all the disorders that are in it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:204795:12"/>3. His sweetness, when he tasts sweetness in any creature, O thinks he then how sweet is he that made it! the Fountain must needs have more than the Stream, <hi>Psal.</hi> 19.1. <hi>The Heavens declare the Glory of God, and the Earth shews his handy work.</hi> Hab. 3.3. <hi>His Glory covered the Heavens, and the Earth was full of his praise,</hi> this makes them Glorifie God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. These Notions put them upon loving him dearly; even above all.</p>
            <p>Do you thus love him? why should you not? seeing his Excellency is above all. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretend to love him, but love their <hi>Lusts</hi> above him; they love him not at all, and many mens Notions of him are such as make them either hate him or fly from him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. but gracious Souls love to give him the Glory of his Grace and Mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O its not every one that has a Right No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of pardoning Mercy; but they that have it love him dearly: and this Love of theirs, is not only of a restraining, but a constraining nature; it constrains them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all good, having had discoveries of God in a covenant of Grace, of God in Christ,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204795:12"/> and of God as a Father sitting upon a Throne of Grace: Hence these affections are begotten in them. Christ is called the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> yea, <hi>the brightness of his Glory,</hi> Heb. 1.3, 4. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9, 10, 11. the <hi>Glory of God the Father,</hi> he is the Glass of the Father. Gods Glory is to be seen plainly in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, both in his Person, Miracles &amp; Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine. The Saints see much of the Glory of God in the work of Redemption, in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation and Intercession of Christ; and this makes them love him, <hi>Psal.</hi> 104:34. their thoughts are sweet of him, and for this end, God has given you his Name in <hi>Exod:</hi> 34:7: that you might know and love him. His Name ought not to be in vain to us, we are not to think of it in vain, or think of it with trouble, as the Psalmist under Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation did, <hi>Psal:</hi> 77:3. <hi>I remembred God and was troubled, but we should think of him with delight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. These Notions of God (when Right) put them upon Trusting in him duely;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea though he slay them, they will trust in him; Job.</hi> 13.15. they give him glory by Leaving their <hi>(All)</hi> with him, and Laying
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204795:13"/> their <hi>(All)</hi> upon him. Sometimes when you know a man to be faithful, you will say, I could venture all upon such a mans word. <hi>What time they are afraid, they trust in him, Psal.</hi> 56.3. Its a sign they know his name, <hi>Psal.</hi> 9.10. Are there any that trust not in him? They know him not; for they that know him, will put their Trust in him, and that at all times, when not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Temptation, <hi>Psal.</hi> 62.8.</p>
            <p>They have had such Discoveries made to them of his Truth, Faithfulness, Power, and Promises, in Christ, that they cannot but give him the glory of them, by Trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him; <hi>Abraham</hi> is said to glorify God by believing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20. (and it's no small mercy that God will account him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self glorified by you, though it be but by one act of Faith.) The Word is called his glory, but chiefly the Gospel, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise (which especially is the ground of Faith) is called the glory of God, or the Glorious Gospel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. and he is said <hi>To Magnifie his Word above all his Name,</hi> Psal. 138.2.</p>
            <p>Many things which are the ground of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204795:13"/> our Trust and Comfort, are called the Glory of God, As</p>
            <p n="1">1. Pardoning mercy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.2. It's his Glory to Conceal a thing; and that (as some think) is meant of pardoning sin by the Antithesis; its the honour of princes to search out a matter; that is evil matter, some Treacherous matter: when God pardons he Conceals or covers sin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Redemption of lost man is said to glorify God <hi>Isai.</hi> 61.1, 2, 3. <hi>that he may be glorified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Gods goodness and gracious nature is called his glory, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.18, 19. <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee shew me thy glory,</hi> says Moses; <hi>I will cause all my goodness to pass before thee</hi> says God: thats good news for us, for its that we stand the most in need of; and <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Its called Riches of glory, that is of grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The coming of Christ is called the glory of God <hi>Isai.</hi> 40.5. its meant of the Righteousness of Christ that is offered in the Gospel.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Ark of the Covenant 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. <hi>last</hi> nay the place where his Gospel is preached
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204795:14"/> is called the place where his honour dwells in <hi>Psal.</hi> 26.8. his Mercy and his Arme is sufficient for your Trust <hi>Psal.</hi> 52.8. <hi>I trust in the mercy of God,</hi> Isai. 51.5 <hi>on my Arme shall they trust.</hi> The tokens of Christs grace and power are called his glory, <hi>John</hi> 1.14 <hi>John</hi> 11.40.</p>
            <p n="4">4: These Notions and Apprehensions put them upon fearing him filially, <hi>Hos.</hi> 3:5:</p>
            <p>Though they have never so much of a Spirit of Adoption yet they cannot but fear him; they have had such Discoveries of his Greatness and Purity that they fall down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, <hi>Rev:</hi> 15:4. <hi>Jer:</hi> 10:7.</p>
            <p n="5">5 These Notions put them upon Admir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Adoring him inwardly and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively.</p>
            <p>Every converted Soul is an admiring Soul; and they account every thing in <hi>God,</hi> and about him to be wonderful.</p>
            <p>Do you thus know what it is to lye in the dust at his feet and admire him? Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration is the running over of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, whereby the Soul is as it were lost in <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204795:14"/>
            <p>When God at any time puts forth an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, there is a wonderful Glory attends it; as when he puts forth acts of Justice on his and the Churches Enemies; <hi>Numb:</hi> 14:21. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 28:22. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 29:13.</p>
            <p>So on the other hand, when he puts forth acts of Grace and Mercy to his poor Church there is a wonderful glory attends it, <hi>Psal:</hi> 85:9. <hi>that Glory may dwell in our Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These are the suitable Dispositions that you are to have if you would evidence your notions of God to be right; and prove your selves to be them that glorifie God. And especially this of Admiration: there is none like God, therefore none to be so admired, all Right worship is full of Admiration.</p>
            <p>Gracious Souls cannot but admire God, and all the wayes he hath taken with them; (and this also make them admire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in a contrary sence, <hi>viz:</hi> in their own vileness and unworthiness, and that they are out of hell.)</p>
            <p>And when at any time (though its pity it is so seldom) they have some small tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sient views and discoveries of him as he is now in Heaven, which is (indeed) a place
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204795:15"/> of Glory they can't but fall admiring of him; and say, <hi>Oh! what a day will that be when God shall come to be Glorified in his Saints, and admired in (all) them that believe,</hi> 2 Thes. 1.10. Heaven is such a place of glory that its called glory it self in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>last Luk.</hi> 24.26.</p>
            <p>And when they view God as in Heaven (where he especially is gloriously revealed) <hi>by an eye of Faith;</hi> they cry out <hi>he is all glorious and their worship is spent in Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when their Apprehensions are Ripen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they come to hope much, as well as love and fear much, they rejoyce in hope of the Glory of God, <hi>Rom</hi> 5.2. and though the day of Judgment be such a terror to the wicked yet to poor Souls that have saving Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions of God, its the day of their hopes and expectations.</p>
            <p>And they glorifie God by marvelling, <hi>Mat:</hi> 9.8. they may well admire Heaven, for if all the glory and splendor of this lower World should be made to pass by Heaven-Gates, the glorified Souls there would not think it worth one glance or cast of their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204795:15"/> eye in comparison of the Glory they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is now the first Branch, viz. suitable affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Branch, Suitable Impressions before him. These will sink deep into the Soul if your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God be right. And these are begun in their first Conversion when their hearts are pricked, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. they lie much under the sence and feeling of God, he works in them such wonderful Impressions of his Greatness, Soveraignty, Holiness, Goodness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as are never worn out, but are maintained and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased in them to their very dying day They have deep and abiding Impressions of all the blessed Attributes of God, but especially of those three, his <hi>Greatness, Holiness, and Goodness.</hi> This might now.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us see whether we have Glorified God or no, and be in stead of a Use of Trial to us, what are our Notions and Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions of God? have they had this bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed effect upon us? have they produced such Dispositions as those before named, and these deep and lasting Impressions yea or no?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:204795:16"/>2. It might also serve to direct us how we may come to Glorifie God, <hi>viz. By get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting right Notions and Apprehensions of Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It might greatly shame us, that the best of us have no more Glorified God, and done so little this way: may we not all of us now lay our hand upon our mouths, and put our mouths in the dust for this? The best has done little, and many have done nothing, they have not glorified God at all, nay it may be many have very much dishonoured him, and done much against his declarative glory though they cannot hurt his essential glory; this is matter of shame and Lamentation.</p>
            <p>This might also reprove many that make false Representations of God, or such as walk not up to their right Notions of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is matter of Comfort to all such as so apprehend of God as you have heard; <hi>that God will account himself Glorified by you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many never drew so near to God in all their lives as rightly to apprehend of him; but if you have been thus happy to draw so
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204795:16"/> near to him as to have such apprehensions of him that have made you, Love him, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire him, and prefer him above all, and love Heaven because it is a place where you shall do nothing else but glorifie him; then have you glorified him.</p>
            <p>Does He come into your hearts often, and make himself known to you? does he lead you along guiding your hand, and break in upon you with glorious Discoveries of himself, as a God and King of Glory? <hi>Acts</hi> 7.2. <hi>the God of Glory appeared to Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Psal.</hi> 24.7, 8. there is a fair pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise made <hi>you, that he will come in if you shut him not out by Ignorance, Ʋnbelief, Impenitency and Obstinacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is called <hi>the Father of Glory,</hi> Eph. 1.17. and his eyes are called <hi>the eyes of his Glory,</hi> which makes gracious Souls afraid to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him, <hi>Isai.</hi> 3.8. Christ is called <hi>the Lord of Glory,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8. have you closed with him? then have you <hi>Glorified God</hi> and may be comforted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So much for the first thing of the three what it is to Glorifie God; we come to the second;</hi> To Glorifie God is this,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:204795:17"/>2. When the Glory of God is plainly to be seen upon the outward face of our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment and our deportment, or of our worshiping God, and walking before him.</p>
            <p>There are two Branches in this Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Branch, When the Glory of God is plainly to be seen upon the face of our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment, the Worship of God ought to be so managed by you, as that others may see Gods holiness upon you in it, and fall in love with it.</p>
            <p>When your Postures, Gestures and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions are such as beget such high though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of God in others as you pretend to in your selves.</p>
            <p>No doubt this is included in the Text, thô it be not mainly meant, <hi>Whatsoever you do, &amp;c.</hi> and if we are to glorifie God in eating and drinking, much more in our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship.</p>
            <p>And other Scriptures speaks it more plain, <hi>Psal.</hi> 29.12. if our natural and civil Actions should Glorifie God, much more our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Actions. Your Worship in secret
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204795:17"/> should be so performed, as that you may believe your selves to be serious and in good earnest.</p>
            <p>And so when you Worship God with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, you should so manage it, as that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may <hi>Glorifie Gods Holiness upon your account.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not <hi>to Worship God in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> but to do it slightly and carelesly, is a sad sight, and a God-dishonouring thing, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Before all the People I will be Glorified;</hi> but alas! how little is this minded by most Worshipers? how few are made in love with Worship through the zeal of others in it?</p>
            <p>But might they not rather say of some kind of vain Worshipers, that they are <hi>Mad?</hi> As 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23.</p>
            <p>Many read their Bibles with no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion than they would a <hi>Play-Book,</hi> and say their Prayers (as they call it) just like <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats</hi> that have learnt to talk, and understand not what they say: this is a great dishonour to God, and is hardening to others. The vain, idle way of <hi>Popish Worshiping,</hi> has stood in the way of the conversion of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204795:18"/>
               <hi>Jews,</hi> and of the <hi>Mahometan World</hi> a great while.</p>
            <p>And as for others, most mens Religion is the fruit of their conceits; they little think that every word they read has Gods Image, and Gods Authority stamped upon it.</p>
            <p>But while I am thus calling upon you <hi>to Glorifie God before others in your Worship,</hi> do not mistake me, do not with the <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees, do all this to be seen of Men; but do all with a sence of God, and of Eternity upon your spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I have five Words to say to you, <hi>viz. that you would labour to Glorifie God,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In your <hi>Confession of Sin,</hi> which is one part of Prayer. Let <hi>the glory of God be seen in it, that others may be provoked by your seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness herein to count sin an odious thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That you would take heed of complementing with God and so lose all your Prayers,</hi> as too many do, <hi>they confess their sins as coldly as they committed them boldly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let Conscience be witness to this: do you not often confess them so coldly that even your selves scarce believe your selves
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204795:18"/> to be in good earnest? That man glorifies God in confession of sin, that does it with self-loathing and shame, even for those sins which none but God can charge him withal. Its not every Confession that <hi>glorifies God, Josh.</hi> 7.19. <hi>give glory to God by confessing,</hi> do it so as your selves and others (when they joyn with you) may believe you hate it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In your begging of Mercy from God, labour in this part of Prayer to <hi>glorifie God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas! how few beg as if they were in earnest, as a Subject would beg favour from his Prince? or a <hi>Poor Tenant</hi> a boon from his Land-lord, or a <hi>poor starving Creature</hi> would beg for an Alms, or a Malefactor for a Pardon from his Judge?</p>
            <p>Do you know the worth of Pardoning Mercy when you pray for it? &amp; so of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther spiritual mercies? do you so pray for mercies as others may believe that you esteem them worth asking and waiting for, and that you are at the right door?</p>
            <p>It is an excellent thing when you <hi>strive</hi> with God in Prayer, both in secret and with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204795:19"/> others, that you beg so humbly, confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and importunately, that others may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that you are at the <hi>door</hi> where ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Mercy dwells; and that God only is the God of all grace and comfort, and that you are for other kind of things than profits, pleasures and preferments here, but that <hi>you are for Blessings indeed,</hi> as he was in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.10: <hi>O that thou wouldest bless me indeed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In your Blessing and giving thanks to God for mercies already received, Do this so as that God may be glorified. This the Scripture is full of, I shall only hint at it; but you see how God accounts of it in <hi>Psal.</hi> 50. <hi>ult. Whoso offereth praise glorifieth me:</hi> and <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.15. <hi>He glorified God,</hi> and Christ sayes, <hi>He gives glory to God,</hi> ver. 18. that was, <hi>he gave Thanks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> might show you how all these three parts of Prayer Glorify God in all his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, his Omnisciency, Soveraignty, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but I forbear enlargement▪ But in giving praise, you are to set the Crown upon the right head; when God puts any glory upon you, by making use of you, &amp; you
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204795:19"/> give it back to him again▪ then do you glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify him; Luke 19.16. <hi>Lord, thy pound hath gained Ten:</hi> and when you say, as 1 Cor. 15.10. <hi>By the grace of God I am, what I am,</hi> and <hi>I Laboured more abundantly, yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me;</hi> and as Gen. 41.16. <hi>it is not in me, God shall give</hi> Pharaoh <hi>an answer of Peace;</hi> and Acts 3.12, 13, 16. he puts power and holiness together. <hi>It's not by our own power and Holiness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's excellent to do much, and yet to be nothing in our own eyes; 1 Chron. 29 11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That was the Proclamation when Christ came, <hi>Glory to God in the Highest!</hi> Peace and Good-will is for us, but Glory or God Alone, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.14</p>
            <p>But some glorify themselves <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.7. There is a Dreadful Doom concerning them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In your spending the Lords-Day, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour so to carry your selves, that Gods Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry may be seen in it.</p>
            <p>It is a Day set apart only for Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship; but, oh this is an undoing thing That our Sabbaths smell so rank of our Week-days! and the great reason, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we have so little Tincture of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204795:20"/> Sabbath in the Week-days.</p>
            <p>The Lords-Day is seriously, (the whole of it) to be spent with him, either in our Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sets, Families, or in the House of God. See what the Prophet says, <hi>Isa.</hi> 58.13. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring</hi> and <hi>Glorifying</hi> is the same.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In your ordinary Discourse, you are to speak</p>
            <p n="1">1. Reverently, And</p>
            <p n="2">2. Magnifyingly of God; then do you cause his Glory to be seen in the face of your Acknowledgment when you do thus.</p>
            <p>A word to each of these:</p>
            <p n="1">1. When we speak of God, we are to speak with great Reverence and Seriousness, that others may be Affected and Edified therewith. Not after a slighty careless manner. As a man may dishonour God by prophane speeches, so he may also, by the manner of his speaking of good things. Many gracious Souls, have had an holy Awe and Dread on their Spirits, upon their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mentioning the Name of God, in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it self; so tender have they been of it, that they have been afraid to abound in using that great Name too frequently, even
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204795:20"/> in their Prayers: How horrible a thing then is it to bring that most Fearful and Glorious Name into matter of Jests? Oh, it's too great and Sacred a Thing to be thus brought into your mouths.</p>
            <p>It's the Temper of a gracious Soul, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to have a secret Reverence attending every word it speaks of God, either before, or after the speaking of it. And this Les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son was Taught it at its first Conversion.</p>
            <p>You may as truly dishonour God, by speaking lightly of what is good, as by speaking evil. You should la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>r to Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify God, both with your mind and your mouth; and excite others so to do also by your doing it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.6.</p>
            <p>And upon this account <hi>David</hi> calls his Tongue his glory so often in the Psalms, and it is your glory when you use it to the glory of God: But the Lord knows it may well be called many a mans shame.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are to speak Magnifyingly of God, we should Extoll him, and Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him to others; and Ascribe greatness to him, goodness and holiness to him; and to say as Rev. 4. last <hi>Thou art worthy, O
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204795:21"/> Lord to Receive Glory, &amp;c:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Psalms abound to this purpose; (the Reading frequently of which <hi>I</hi> commend to you) see <hi>Psal.</hi> 86 9. <hi>Psal.</hi> 105.1, 2, 3. <hi>Talk ye of all his wondrous works;</hi> Psal. 145 6, 11. Psal. 35. last. 1 Pet. 4.11. <hi>If any man speak, let him speak as the Oracles of God; that God in all things may be glorifyed.</hi> Though this may be meant especially of an Authoritative way of speaking in the name of God, yet it may include the other; <hi>Paul</hi> concludes his Epistle to the <hi>Romans</hi> with <hi>giving glory to God.</hi> See <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.20 <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.21.</p>
            <p>But how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould others glorify God on your account, when you speak lightly, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or discouragedly of God?</p>
            <p>So much of the first Branch, when the Glory of God is to be seen upon the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward face of our Acknowledgment.</p>
            <p>The second Branch, when the Glory of God is plainly seen upon the outward face of our Deportment, or our Conversation; then indeed do we Glorify God.</p>
            <p>This is mainly and especially meant in the Text, though the other is included also: It's not enough to have high and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204795:21"/> thoughts of God in our hearts, and also to perform a seeming zealous Worship to him, but these things are to be diffused a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into our Lives and Conversations, that others may see by our holy Lives, that the God we worship is an Holy God. Else how are we said to glorify God? and how came others by observing us, <hi>to glorify our Father which is in Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's not enough to be serious alone, others know not what we do there, but we must bring our Religion out of our Closets, into our Shops, Houses, and Fields; we are not only to be Religions in Gods House, but in our own Houses also. Athiestical Livers are great Enemies to a God-head.</p>
            <p>But then do you glorify God, when your words, ways, course, and Discourse, give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers a fair occasion to lift up the Name of God in their Hearts. You ought not only to serve God your selves, but to carry it so, as to win others to God; carry it so, as that others may know there is a God, and that he is a very Holy God; that their Hearts may thereby be raised up to God, that they may begin to Admire, Adore,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204795:22"/> Observe Love, &amp; walk in the fear of this God.</p>
            <p>Our Loves and our Lives ought to be like flames, catching hold of all about us.</p>
            <p>No doubt there are thousands in Heaven, that are Blessing God for the holy Lives of others. All Gods Attributes are his glory, but especially his Holiness: therefore when much of this is seen upon the face of our Deportment, then do we very much glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy God. He is said to be <hi>glorious in Holi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ness;</hi> this Attribute runs through all his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Attributes, he is infinitely Holy in them all: And if Holiness be the glory of God, why should it not be our glory? <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.11. And he is not only glorious in Holiness, but he glories in it: he is called Holy three times together, <hi>Rev</hi> 4.8. <hi>Isa.</hi> 6.3. he is infinitely happy in his Holiness, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13. Sin never yet had a good look from him, nor ever will. <hi>David</hi> smarted severely for it, and all the Saints that fell into it ever since, have smarted for it, more or less: God hates it, and the workers of it, and the Saints know it, Psal. 5.4, 5. <hi>Thou hatest all the workers of iniquity.</hi> He will have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing about him, but what is holy; his Son,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204795:22"/> Angels, Sabbaths, are called holy; and he has also willed and commanded you to be Holy, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. Be Holy, as he is, for quality, though not for quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity: Hence by these inward Affections, Impressions, and holy Conversations, we are said to sanctifie him, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.3. that is, by Recommending him to others Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by your God-glorifying Conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. <hi>you are to be holy in all manner of Conversation;</hi> which takes in both our Relative Duties, and our Callings, Conditions and Company.</p>
            <p>You read <hi>of the Beauties of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;</hi> and indeed the more Holiness, the more beauty in any: Holiness puts a Beauty upon any, let them otherwise be never so mean or deformed.</p>
            <p>The more there is of three things in your Deportment, the more is God glorifyed by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The more there is of God in your Deportment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The more there is of Christ in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The more there is of Heaven in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The more there is of God in your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204795:23"/> (or your Conversation) the more is he glorifyed; he is glorifyed by nothing, but what is of himself <hi>Adam</hi> was made after Gods Image, that is in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; and this carries Reverence in it from the worst of men, whose Consciences ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour it, though their wills and affections hate it. Then does a man glorify God, when <hi>Holiness to the Lord is engraven upon all his Faculties, and all his Affa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs upon all the Faculties of his Soul, Mind, Will, Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Affections, though this is invisible to men▪ but he glorif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es God in his Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when its plainly written upon his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,</hi> and there will such a day come <hi>when Holiness to the Lord shall be upon the Hors<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Bridles, and every Pot in Jerusalem shall be holy,</hi> &amp;c. Zech. 14.20, 21. A vain jungling Spirit is not becoming a Christian, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be always Jesting, this is not to be used as your Ordinary Food, though mirth be <hi>allowed sometimes, yet it is to be used with great sobriety and moderation. God is (as one well saith) the real glory of every thing, person, word or work; if God be not in your Health, Houses, Relations, Employments;</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:204795:23"/> and in every word you speak, and every work you do, there is no glory in it; if it have not more or less reference to God it is worth nothing.</p>
            <p>And you may know if Gods Glory be to be seen in your Conversation by these things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>When you are afraid to offend God tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> none know of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>When it appears to others (as far as they can judge) that Gods Glory is your only Rule to walk by, both in Heart, Lip and Life, in Thoughts, Words and Actions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>When it appears (as far as they can see) to others, that in your whole Conversation you are swayed by the consideration of eternal and invisible things, and you carry and look like men that believe unseen and eternal things, and consult not Profits, Honours, Ease,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>When it appears to others that you only live to God; that his Glory is that you live for, and that his Work you mind, and that you place your whole happiness in his favour, and make it your only business to please him in all you do, and it appears that you mind Gods work more than your own; and that you carry
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204795:24"/> towards him as your Owner and Benefactor, and as one with whom you expect to live for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The more of Christ there is in your Conversation the more God is glorified by you.</p>
            <p>Christ is the glory of God, and hath wonderfully glorified him.</p>
            <p>Gods Glory did most eminently appear in him when he was upon Earth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14. &amp; 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. <hi>The Father also was glorified by him, Joh.</hi> 17.4. <hi>I have glorified thee on Earth,</hi> &amp;c. let the same mind be in you that was in Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, when you show forth the vertues of Christ, then you glorifie God. God loves Christ, and his Image in him, it is so like himself, like Loves its like, we use to say, <hi>John</hi> 14.8. <hi>He that hath seen me hath seen the Father also.</hi> If the Father had been clothed with flesh he would have carried just as Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ did.</p>
            <p>God accounts a Christ-like spirit of great price. To be sweet, patient, charitable, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, useful, evangelical in all we do, to be fruitful in every good work is to be like Christ, and you show your selves to have the spirit of Christ by the fruits of it. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204795:24"/> 22, 23. 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 3.4. he had been in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before recommending Christs Example, and here tells you such a spirit is of great price in Gods sight? and <hi>John</hi> 15.8. <hi>Herein is my Father glorified,</hi> and <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. <hi>We are so to glorifie God, as that others may fall a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so too.</hi> Phil. 1.11. the glory of God and of Christ are put together, <hi>John</hi> 1.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.4.</p>
            <p>He was a great Example of Seriousness and Gravity when he was on Earth; you often read of his <hi>Groaning, Weeping,</hi> &amp;c. but never can you produce that Chapter or Verse that speaks of his jesting or laughing away his time; he tells us <hi>he came to do the will of him that sent him, and to finish his work.</hi> And what a serious patern was he in his Preaching! though very plain in it, yet never Man spake like him; O his tenderness, weeping over Sinners! and his great in offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siveness to all, and what a wonderful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of Humility was he! especially when he washed his Disciples feet: hence he invites you to learn of him, <hi>John</hi> 13. from <hi>v.</hi> 4. to the 15th. <hi>Do as I have done to you,</hi> Mat. 11.29. <hi>Learn of me for I am meek and lowly in heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:204795:25"/>
            <p>And for his Obedience to the Law, he was a meer Commentary upon it, and for pleasing of God what an Example was he! <hi>I do alwayes the things that please him;</hi> and for his Charity and Love, how did he feed Multitudes! and for Self-denial and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the World what a rare instance was he? <hi>John</hi> 6.15. <hi>When he perceived they would come and take him by force to make him a King, he departed,</hi> &amp;c. he was not fond (as many are) of great preferments, but steals away from them: &amp; for patience, how many reproaches did he bear? altho' they were very grievous to his most tender Spirit, in somuch that he sayes in <hi>Psal.</hi> 69 20. <hi>it had broken his heart,</hi> for this is spoken of <hi>Christ,</hi> of <hi>David</hi> only in the Type.</p>
            <p>And for meekness, how do you find him riding upon an Asses Colt, he slighted all the Pomps and Bravery of the World when his Disciples showed him the goodly Stones wherewith the Temple was adorned, how little did he regard them!</p>
            <p>Carry like this meek humble crucified Christ, if you would glorifie God.</p>
            <p>The contrary of all this that you have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204795:25"/> heard does greatly dishonour God.</p>
            <p>How many are witness that your Christ-like Conversation has made them to glorifie God? do you verily think in your Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that Christ would carry as you do, in such and such particulars which you best know of? that he would so vainly squander away his time in mirth and jolity, and vain and wicked company? do you think that he would spend his time in jesting, telling idle Tales, in laughing and sporting? not but that a man may laugh, for it is a power of Gods creating: but by this I mean a giving up your selves to live in carnal pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure, and to let out your hearts unto such things as these.</p>
            <p>It is true many acts of Christ were not imitable by us, as his sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>fying Justice, his forty dayes Fast, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but as he was an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of all manner of Holiness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we are to walk as he walked as much as in us lies; you ought to speak and walk as he did, else why are you called Christians? have you not important work that lies on your hands? why should you not (as he did) labour to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch it? <hi>John</hi> 9.4. <hi>I must work the works of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204795:26"/> him that sent me while it is called to day, the might cometh wherein none can work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You see how carefully he improved his season, and can you for shame bear the name of Christians and spend your time in Card<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Dicing, Drinking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O this ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes you, and this is not to glorifie God in your deportment. To be slighty and careless and slothful about those things that are in themselves good, is not to be like Christ, and so glorifies not God.</p>
            <p>I have read of one that was naturally of a proud stout Spirit, who was converted by reading that passage of Christs washing his Disciples Feet, and cried out, <hi>Lord, thou hast overcome me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have also read of some Philosophers that were so beloved of their Scholars, that they would labour to imitate them even in their infirmities out of pride, but you have such a patern to imitate that is infinitely free of all infirmities: one should think we should be very ambitious of such an example; no marvel that his Life was serious and holy, for his nature was so. And O what A patern was he for Ministers, in his rising a great while
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204795:26"/> before day, that he might not by his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick work be hindred from his private com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, &amp; it is said, that at some times he continued all night in Prayer.</p>
            <p>He was a notable Example also for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving outward Occurrences to a spiritual use, which appears in all his Parables, and many of his other Speeches, and all this was written for our Example, see what a serious charge we have in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2: <hi>Looking unto Jesus,</hi> that is, <hi>as our Principle, and as our patern.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we are to have much of Christ for our Example in our conversation, of which you will see farther, under one of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.</p>
            <p>And to make him our Principle, as you will see afterwards in the Directions.</p>
            <p>So much of the Second Particular as to our Deportment or Conversation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The more of heaven there is to be seen in the face of our Deportment, the more is God glorified by us in it. Then do we glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God when we look not like men of this World, as too many do. You are to carry
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204795:27"/> so as if your business were in Heaven, your Trade and Traffick there, and as Citizens of the new <hi>Jerusalem. Phil.</hi> 3.20. But the worldly, carnal lives of Professors are a great dishon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to God. If there were much of Heaven in our conversation, it would convince the most sensual and bruitish Persons we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse with, that there is another World, which ought to be preferred before this World; and this would make them to wish to dye your death, though they could not get up to live your lives. Let them see that you seek an unseen happiness, that you veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly look to live with Christ; let all see what you are, and whether you are going. If you be Believers live up to the hopes and priviledges of Believers, let all see that your hopes are bound up in the second coming of Christ, that others may see by you that Heaven is worth venturing all for, and that there is a Reward for the Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous.</p>
            <p>Let them see that you account self-seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be self-undoing, and that <hi>that</hi> time that is not lived to God is lost, that what is done for God is done for ever, that this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204795:27"/> Life is short and uncertain, and that the Life to come is certain and eternal; and let it be seen, that you are by little and little Transplanting and Transporting thither. There is not a good thought, word, or act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, but if you are in Christ shall meet you beyond the Grave. Be laying up apace then, and let all see that you make Heaven your Home: Live by Faith, and count all things here nothing. Scorn the <hi>Worldlings</hi> happiness, though ever so great, accounting the Lives of <hi>such</hi> Base and Contemptible, and that Riches, Honours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are poor things in comparison of what you are seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, and hoping for, and that you are contented to endure Afflictions, as <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are not worthy to be compared with the future glory,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17, 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> see <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. that you believe this Text, and herein God is <hi>glorified</hi> by you, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14, 16. <hi>Isai.</hi> 24.15. That you can <hi>glorifie God in the fire. Let the Life of Jesus hereby be manifested in you,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.10, 11. <hi>And let Christ be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in you, both in Life and Death; Phil.</hi> 1.20. then indeed is God glorified by you, and more eminently when you can get up to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204795:28"/> long for Death and Judgment, and <hi>desire to be absent from the Body, that you may be present with the Lord.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8.</p>
            <p>Let others see that you can live cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the hopes of Heaven, and that your Hopes, Births, and Hearts, are higher than the Highest of Carnal men, though Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs or Emperours. And the more of such an heavenly Conversation you shew, the more is God glorified by you; for in Heaven he is perfectly glorified. Oh la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to live like the <hi>Triumphant Church,</hi> though you be yet in the <hi>Militant.</hi> Great degrees of <hi>Grace</hi> are called <hi>Glory</hi> (they look so like it) in 2 Cor. 3.18. <hi>from glory to glory,</hi> that is from one degree of grace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another.</p>
            <p>Believers should be looking-Glasses for others to dress themselves by, then would they be forced to say as Dan. 2.47. <hi>Of a Truth your God is God of Gods, and a Lord of Kings.</hi> This would make them glorifie God on your behalf, Gal. 1. last. and think more highly of God and Heaven, and <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify God for your professed subjection to the Gospel,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13. <hi>Such Trees of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204795:28"/> do glorifie God, Isa.</hi> 6.13. It was the greatest Commendation that a scoffing E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy gave of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> that he could <hi>Breathe forth nothing but Puritanism;</hi> I wish it were true of us all. This would make others <hi>fall down, and confess that God were in us of a Truth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.25. But it is very sad, that when profane persons and Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians are together, all the difference betwixt them is, that they will not Swear or Curse as they do. An Eminent Person says upon the like occasion if a man should hear of one that had the spirit of God, that was united to Christ, filled with all the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of God, whose Conversation were in Heaven, and had God to his Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he would expect very great things from him, not to be entertained with vain Jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or sinful discourse, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but we may well say with <hi>Erasmus, that seeing the World cannot be brought to Christianity;</hi> men have <hi>brought Christianity to the World,</hi> in too great a measure, and with too many. <hi>I</hi> conclude this particular with the definition that the Assembly at <hi>London</hi> gives of a Godly man, that <hi>He is one whose person is united to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204795:29"/> Christ by a Lively Faith, and whose nature is Elevated by the Spirit of Regeneration, and whose Principles and Practices are Supernatural and Divine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May not one then think of many (that count themselves Christians, and would have others to account them more than the common sort) that they only cheat and deceive themselves?</p>
            <p>Thus I have done with the second Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Head how we are said to Glorifie God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The glorifying of God consists in this, when we do (as much as in us lies) act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ually <hi>propose</hi> the glory of God, in our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Actings; and when it is not attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it is heartily bewailed, and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God; and as soon as God meets with these hearty Acknowledgments, he forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with with pardons the Soul. The New Creature is seen in nothing more than in the <hi>bent of his Soul for God,</hi> and his sincere Resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; if you never design thus to glorifie God, it is a certain sign that you are no Christians. And this you ought to do eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day at least, and at the beginning of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Action either Sacred, or Civil, at
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204795:29"/> the beginning of every day, and more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially on the Lords-day: and when you do come short, you ought immediately to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new your sincere Repentance, and Cordial Resolutions. A man in a long Journey, sets out every day for his Journeys End, though he may not think of it every step he goes; thus do you, set out every day for Heaven as your Home, and often in the day think of it, and speak of it; so set out to glorifie God, with a full intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Soul, and carry your End in your Eye. We are to account of God, not only as the first cause, the most Excellent Being, but also as our chiefest Good, and our last End.</p>
            <p>And though we cannot think of this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very step we take, yet we are to set our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces towards it; and though we cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in every thing to glorifie God, yet we are to set it as our Mark to Aim at, in all we do, both at the beginning of the day (as before) and the Lords-day, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a Solemn Duty, or sitting down at our Tables, to eat and drink for the glory of God, going to our Beds, to Rest our
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204795:30"/> selves in order to our serving of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So when we go to visit, or to work at our Callings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This End proposed at the beginning, hath great influence all along, as you see in the throwing of a Stone into the Water, the stone sinks out of sight, but the Circles will remain sometime after; When a Bell has done Ringing, it will sound and shake for some time after; so is it here; if this design of glorifying God be maintained, it will have an influence upon our Actions.</p>
            <p>Here let me give you three words of Advice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be sure that Grace be in the Habit in your Souls, that the bent and biass of the Heart be set aright for God, else all your Resolutions will come to nothing; this work is too hard for an unrenewed, unsanct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ified heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Bring this gracious Habit into act, by a Renewed Resolution, and by frequent E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jaculations to God for Assistance, this do as often as you can.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When you have done thus, take heed of any other inordinate Intention, or Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:204795:30"/> to hinder what you have done in setting out.</p>
            <p>It is said of the <hi>Nazarite,</hi> Numb. 6.12. <hi>All the days of his Separation that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were lost, because it was defiled.</hi> So here it spoils all. Moses <hi>was offered a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er bribe than ordinary, by the Lord; and yet he would not take it, because he minded the glory of God, more than his own, that was the End he kept his Eye upon,</hi> Numb. 14.11, 12. <hi>But do not you Eat to your selves? that is bad,</hi> God would have you not only to <hi>fast unto him, but to eat unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it the great design of your Soul to glorifie God, the one thing you do? That runs through your very Soul; bearing all other things down before it. Psal. 27.4. Phil. 3.14. <hi>Do you make all things beside to stoop to this Renewed purpose of your Soul?</hi> You see how faulty <hi>Jehu</hi> was in this, and the Pharisees they did not propose Gods Glory, but themselves, in what they did, do you spend every day as for God and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity? and thus propose Gods glory; &amp; well you may, for the meanest Action thus done, shall be well Rewarded, Col. 3.23,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:204795:31"/> 24. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6:5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Any such Relative Duties if done to the glory of God, shall be Rewarded, Rom.</hi> 14.6, 7, 8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21. <hi>if you don't thus live to Christ, Death will never be your Gain.</hi> God took it very ill from <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li's</hi> Sons, that they served themselves first out of the Sacrifices, 1 Sam. 2.14, 15. In all our Actions God is to be uppermost in our designs, and in Spiritual Actions he is to be <hi>All.</hi> God should be the end of all our operations; all our motions should Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in him (but when self lies at the bottom all is nought.) This is called a doing,</p>
            <p n="1">1: All in the Name of Christ, Col. 3.17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And a being devoted to his Fear, Psal. 119.38.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A being in the Fear of the Lord all the day long, Prov. 23.17.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A walking up and down in his Name, Zach. 10. last. That is a blessed Promise indeed, has God made it good to you?</p>
            <p>We should (as one saith well) every morning set out on a right point of the compass, for if we set out wrong it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangers
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:204795:31"/> our going wrong all the day, the best that can come of it is loss of time and pains, if a Clock or Watch be wound up and set right in the morning, with good keeping, it will go well all the day. <hi>David</hi> used thus to set out, Psal. 5.3. <hi>In the morning will I direct my prayer unto thee and look up, Psal.</hi> 139.18. <hi>When I am awake I am still with thee.</hi> A mans last End is but one, and ought to be no other than this to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God, though subordinate ends may be minded in their proper places, yet alwayes with respect and tendency to the ultimate end, and they ought to be wholly laid aside when they interfere with <hi>that,</hi> or that it come to be hindred by <hi>them.</hi> Our health, wealth, mirth, liberty, life and all are to give way to the last end; and for the want of thus doing, God charges <hi>Eli</hi> with <hi>honouring his Sons before him,</hi> the subordinate end prevailed above the ultimate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thus I have showed you in general</hi> what it is to Glorifie God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next thing propounded <hi>is to show what
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:204795:32"/> it is to Glorifie God in eating and drinking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the second part of the Text, and it may also include all kind of Recreations lawful in themselves, thô not named.</p>
            <p>As cessation from Labour, Visiting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for much of pleasure is set forth by Eating &amp; Drinking, yea Heaven it self is often set forth by it. So that I may put all these things together, though not so particularly meant in the Text, Recreations, Diversions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Eating and Drinking all these <hi>are to be done to the Glory of God,</hi> and not only in greater Meals of Feasting, but even in our common Meals it should be thus, (so that by the way it will follow, that we should do it in every thing) we cannot glorifie God in unlawful Sports, I hope none of you will think so, as <hi>Cards, Dice,</hi> &amp;c. nor those Sports that have either cruelty or costliness in them; things unlawful cannot be made lawful, let your end be ever so good, See <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>last. have pleasure</hi> in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither holy things nor sinful things should be matter of our Sport.</p>
            <p>I need to say but little here, because what has been said before may save me the labour,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:204795:32"/> if persons glorifie God as is said in those three Particulars, they will do it in this.</p>
            <p>Only a few words briefly here:</p>
            <p>It lies in three things, our Eying and our Glorifying of God,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In the Introduction of them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In the Progression.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>In the Conclusion of them.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We are to <hi>Eye and Glorifie God</hi> in the Introduction of them, in our first setting upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> put all Recreations under this of <hi>Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Drinking</hi> for brevity sake, though we are not to use Eating and Drinking on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Recreation, I mean for pleasure, but to strengthen us for Service, but most of some persons pleasure and outward Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is at their Tables; and Heaven as I told you is set off by it, not that we should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of Heaven as of a <hi>Fools Paradise,</hi> or <hi>Elysian Fields,</hi> to consist in carnal, sensual delights, but the Holy Ghost is pleased to make use of this similitude, to set off the pleasure they have there, to let us know
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:204795:33"/> that they have unspeakably more pleasure in Communion with God than we have in <hi>Eating and Drinking.</hi> Now when we begin upon our <hi>Eating,</hi> &amp;c. we should keep our Eye upon the Glory of God, we should so intend and resolve by the Grace of God to eat this Meal for the Glory of God, use this Recreation, unstring the Bow now, only to be more fit for his service by it; if the Bow should alwayes stand bent, it would not be fit for use: and though such a course as this might be hard at first, yet the more you are acquainted with it, the more skill &amp; strength you would get for it.</p>
            <p>And this would not destroy your chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness: how can this Text be otherwise expounded? if we are not thus to begin our Meals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is very sad when we have no higher an end in <hi>Eating,</hi> &amp;c. than a Beast, to satisfie our sensual Appetite. In natural Actions, you are to have supernatural ends: you are not to walk abroad because you have nothing else to do, or to eat only because you are hungry, but you are to Glorifie God in it, and do it to fit you the more for your gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:204795:33"/> and particular calling, and your crazy carcasses stand in need of some sober, short and seasonable Diversion, and God is no hard Master, he allows you this, he has given us many things, not only for necessity but for delight, yea all things richly to enjoy. Nay he bids you by <hi>Solomon</hi> to <hi>Recreate your selves,</hi> Eccles. 9.7, 8, 9. he speaks not like an Epicure as some might vainly think, for he in the 7nth verse gives the Reason, <hi>God hath accepted thy work.</hi> (Note by the way that wicked men have no right to any Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and they abuse them as they do every thing else:) but some are blamed for not tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that lawful comfort in what they enjoy, and it is counted a sore evil, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 6.2, 3. not to rejoyce soberly in what they have, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 2.24. and 3.12. its called the <hi>gift of God so to do.</hi> We are allowed to get (as well as commanded to do) all the good we can while we are here, and some persons need Recreations more than others, and are to use them out of duty. I forbear to name such, most persons are too forward this way.</p>
            <p>But shall we be as without God in the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:204795:34"/> world when we use Recreations? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. You ought so to intend and begin upon them as to further the Glory of God and your own good account. It was a saying of <hi>Luther, I have formerly eaten and drunk to my self, but now I am resolved by the Grace of God it shall further my good account,</hi> So <hi>Austin, he bewails his eating to himself.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What shall we think then of such Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors that eat to Gluttony, and drink to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess? I beseech you look on it as your duty to Glorifie God in these as well as in Gods House, and in your closets. A curious Scribe will be careful to draw his small Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters exactly as well as his Capital, a good Builder will contrive to do his Kitchin well, as well as his Dining Room; see how God blames them in <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.5, 6. there is great reason why we should eat and drink for God, for he gives us all; do we not daily live on Heavens Expences? it is Gods Wool and Flax we wear, Gods Food and Rayment we enjoy, <hi>Hos.</hi> 2.9. <hi>My Corn, and my Wine, my Wool and my Flax,</hi> sayes God.</p>
            <p>No Christian lives to himself, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.6.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:204795:34"/> as you have all from him and by him, so you are to do all to him, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6, 5.7.</p>
            <p>And when you visit, you should resolve to get or do good, and leave a good savour behind you. So you should eat, drink and sleep to refresh (as one sayes well) <hi>a weary Servant of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Recreations should only be used as sauce to whet our Stomachs, not as our food to live on. You would wonder to see a man whetting his Sythe all the day instead of Mowing; you should use these only as Oyl to the Wheels, to make them go on more readily. Its very sad indeed to do all for to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie your Lusts, or to pass away the Time, you will have Time little enough when you come to dye.</p>
            <p>School-boys learn hard that they may play; but wise men play that they may work.</p>
            <p>This godly Introduction would put you upon asking your Fathers leave for what you do. How often was this used in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? <hi>Shall I go up to Ramoth Gilead? when David had a mind to go against the Philistins,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:204795:35"/> he asks Gods Leave first, so should you,</hi> in every thing you go about. The very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens had a notion of this, <hi>A Jove Principium. Baalam</hi> seems to have something of it <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.8. and in your thus doing, you Acknowledg Gods Dominion and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty over you, and, it argues your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on him also. And as you should ask his Leave, so you should ask his Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing also. <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.12. <hi>That good Servant asks Gods Blessing before he would go on his Errand.</hi> Jer. 10.23 <hi>The way of a man is not in himself; it is not in man that walketh to direct his paths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You should crave a Blessing upon all, or else they are easily cursed to you, <hi>Every thing is Sanctified by the Word and Prayer.</hi> Christ looked up to Heaven before he brake the Bread, if you do not ask Gods Blessing, you may Eat and not be satisfied, (as some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times God threatens) and you may sleep and not be Refreshed, <hi>For it is he that giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Beloved Sleep:</hi> and we should la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to maintain Communion with God in our asking his Blessing. For that is true, Mat. 4.4. <hi>Man lives not by Bread only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:204795:35"/>2. We are to Eye and Glorifie God in our progression in them, in our manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of these things; and that by a frequent Renewing of Ends, and Aims, and by a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Ejaculation to God in them. Your Intention should be often brought thus into act. And you should beware (as was said under one of the General Heads) of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inordinate Intention arising, or prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to hinder this; we are to Eat and drink for Eternal Life, as minding that <hi>one</hi> thing. It is said of <hi>Socrates,</hi> that he did as really benefit his Scholars in their Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as when he was Reading Lectures to them. We are in nothing more apt to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God, than in the midst of Friends, Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; Drinking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And (which is worse) more apt to let down our Watch in good Company than in Bad, but you should take heed of laying aside your seriousness when you go about these things. <hi>Job</hi> was afraid his Children had missed it in their Feasting by forgetting God. <hi>Job</hi> 1.5. for that is it he means, by <hi>Cursing God;</hi> they were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Taught than so, but he means they had forgotten God, or carried unsuitably to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:204795:36"/> his Presence. It is no good sight to see good men themselves extraordinary merry.</p>
            <p>You read of some that feed themselves without fear, Jude 12. <hi>without the fear of God.</hi> You may eat and drink with cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness, but must there be nothing else? See what mad work they make in their mirth, Job 21.12, 13, 14. <hi>They take the Timb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el and Harp, and Rejoice at the sound of the Organ, and they spend their dayes in Mirth,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore they say unto God, <hi>depart from us, &amp;c.</hi> There is dreadful Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage indeed! but a gracious Soul would not be at a Distance from God in any place, or Company. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us <hi>that the way of Life is above to the wise,</hi> and that is a shorter, fairer, safer way than <hi>below.</hi> It is said Exod. 18.12. <hi>They did Eat before God.</hi> We ought continually to keep the sence of the Divine Presence, upon our Souls in all we do, and in all we Enjoy. God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <hi>Abraham to walk before him, and to be Ʋpright.</hi> It is an Excellent thing when it may be said, <hi>That every Pot is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness to the Lord.</hi> And as we are thus to Renew our Ends, and Aims to glorifie
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:204795:36"/> God in our Eating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So we are also to be often breathing forth holy Ejaculations, and Affections to God, in them. That was an excellent Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of an holy Minister, <hi>That to him each Thought was a Prayer, each Prayer a Song, each Day a Sabbath, and each Meal a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> This need not to hinder our moder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate cheerfulness, nor our necessary Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, about other Affairs.</p>
            <p>It is thought, that most of <hi>Solomons Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs were spoken at his Table, and there is a whole Folio Book, written of</hi> Luther's <hi>Table-Talk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If all News, idle Talk, were written in a Book, which many speak at their Tables (as <hi>Plato</hi> would have it) What Volumns of vanity would there be? however Angels take notice, and Conscience Books it all.</p>
            <p>Two of Gods Attributes chiefly are matter for our thoughts at such times, his <hi>Goodness,</hi> and his <hi>All-sufficiency.</hi> His <hi>Goodness,</hi> that so spreads our Table, and fills our Cup, and gives us all things Richly to enjoy, especially in these sad times, when many far better than we, are
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:204795:37"/> deprived of them, how good is He that makes all these good? especially if they come swimming unto us in the blood of Christ.</p>
            <p>And his <hi>Sufficiency,</hi> what a great House-Keeper is he <hi>who opens his hand, and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the desire of every Living Thing! We read of the Primitive Saints they did Eat their Bread with Cheerfulness, and singleness of heart, Acts</hi> 2.46. <hi>they were so delighted with the thoughts of God,</hi> and in <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.25. <hi>They delighted in his Goodness, &amp;c.</hi> It's true, <hi>That Meats and Drinks Commend us not to God, and the Kingdom of God consisteth not in them</hi> (as the Apostle says) but yet you may think of God, and of his Kingdom in the use of them; how often doth Christ give us an Example this way? Luke 14.15: his blessed Discourse Ravishes that man so that he cries out, <hi>Blessed is he that may Eat Bread in the Kingdom of God.</hi> You have his Discourse from the seventh to the fourteenth verse.</p>
            <p>And if you would do thus, it would be the ready way to observe all the other Rules given by Divines about these things, as to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:204795:37"/> do them soberly, moderately and season<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As to the seasons of Recreation, note, they are altogether unseasonable up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lords-day, also when the Church is in Trouble they are less seasonable; the more seldom and short at such a time, the better, Amos 6.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. Isa. 22.12, 13. <hi>You are to Eat and Drink, &amp;c.</hi> so as to be fit to pray. You were not made only for pleasure, as the <hi>Leviathan to sport in the Deeps?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do you only as <hi>Jonathan, that tasted a little Honey on the end of his Rod.</hi> You read of some that live in pleasure upon the Earth, you should do all as persons upon <hi>Earth;</hi> too much mirth suites not <hi>that</hi> state. These things often become Clouds, and Cloggs to us in our way to Heaven, instead of helping us.</p>
            <p>It is said <hi>of those</hi> in <hi>Noahs time, they did Eat, Drank, they Married, &amp;c. as if they did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else. Some are said not to serve the Lord Jesus Christ, but their own Bellies,</hi> that is sad. There is bread and salt at every Feast, so your Discourse should feed, and season others.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:204795:38"/>3. In the conclusion of them you should glorifie God; and that by humble and thankful Reflection. You should look back, and be humbled for your miscarriages, if you have missed it, and thankful for Gods goodness, presence, and help if you have had it. As we are apt to forget God <hi>in,</hi> so <hi>after</hi> them. Christ charges us to beware of Surfeting, &amp;c. because that makes us unmindful of, and unfit for, the great day, Luke 21.34. <hi>Wine, and new Wine take away the heart, Hos.</hi> 4.11. <hi>fulness often breeds forgetfulness, Deut.</hi> 6.11, 12, 13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.10.32.15. Jesurun <hi>waxed fat, and Kicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That was an Excellent Prayer of <hi>Agur,</hi> Prov. 30.9. We are apt to forget God, and Gods poor, when we are <hi>full</hi> our selves, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering little the many naked Backs, and empty Bellies of others. <hi>Christ has bid us send for the poor, Lame, and Blind, to feast them, if we will feast, but few do so? however, tho' we don't send for them, yet we might send unto them.</hi> Great Eaters and Drinkers are seldom Friends to the poor. Few are like <hi>Job, not to eat his Morsel alone,</hi> Job 31.17.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:204795:38"/> but most like churlish <hi>Nabal,</hi> 1 Sam. 25.11. But its bad to be thus forgetful, you would thank your Neighbour for your entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and will you thus Requite God?</p>
            <p>The best way to be thankful is to live well, to do as good Servants, when they have dined they go to their work.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>I</hi> have done with the 2d. thing propounded, what it is to glorifie God in Eating and Drinking? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More might be said, but I leave it.</p>
            <p>As for the third thing to show us why we should thus glorifie God, both in the course of our Lives, and also in our Eating and Drinking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>I</hi> leave to the Use of Exhortation, and the Motives to serve instead of Reasons.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p>There might be divers Uses made from what has been said, But <hi>I</hi> mainly Aim at the Use of Exhortation.</p>
               <p>Tho' here might be a Use of <hi>Information;</hi> or here you may infer from what has been said,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:204795:39"/>1. That Religion is a serious, and indust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thing, there is much to be done, God sent you not into this world as into a Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house, but a Work-house. Religion is not your <hi>by, but your main</hi> business, it is called Running, Fighting, Wrestling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which denotes Labour and Hardship, though plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It informs you, what your work is.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That Religion extends it self to small things comparatively. You are to glorifie God in all places, and in all things.</p>
               <p>Also a word of Reproof, and that</p>
               <p n="1">1. To them that never in all their Lives glorified God; does not your Conscience tell you, you never did it? nay, some carry as if it were their work openly to dishon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our God, O their Wickedness!</p>
               <p n="2">2. To those that though they know God, yet <hi>do not glorifie him as God,</hi> Rom 1.21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To such that instead of glorifying God, glorifie themselves, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.7.</p>
               <p n="4">4 To those that set up others in Gods room, that honour and Love something more than God, 1 Sam. 2.29</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:204795:39"/>3. It might also be an Use of Trial, have you right Apprehensions of God? do you live a holy life? and design the glory of God in your particular Actions?</p>
               <p n="4">4. But the main Use is of Exhortation, and it calls upon us all seriously to mind the glorifying of God, and to make it our great business so to do, both in Heart, Lip and Life, as you have heard at large.</p>
               <p>And begin at your Hearts, else it will all come to nothing. One would think there were no need of Motives, but our backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to it is such that <hi>I</hi> shall give you a few, and subjoyn some Means or Directions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="motive">
               <head>
                  <hi>Motive,</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>This is your great &amp; very important Duty: The Doctrine tells you so, and what have you and <hi>I</hi> to do, as we are Creatures, and Governed by a Law, but to mind our Duty? <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd its not an ordinary Duty, but its</p>
               <p n="1">1. A very weighty Duty, that much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ends upon (to wit) Gods Honour, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>our own comfort.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An absolute indispensible Duty, the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:204795:40"/> neglect of this can never be dispensed with, though some other Duties have for a time been dispensed with, as Circumcision, and the Passeover, when the People were in the Wilderness, because God loves <hi>Mercy</hi> rather than <hi>Sacrifice:</hi> but his Glory he cannot give to another; he will have his Glory whatever he wants, he sayes <hi>Psal.</hi> 50. <hi>last, Thou shalt Glorifie me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. This is the most reasonable &amp; accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Duty in the World, as its indispensible, so its indisputable, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1, God is well pleased with it. Its a plain Duty, some Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are dark, but this is not; its a right Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and no fault is to be found in it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reasonable, and its brought in with a <hi>Therefore</hi> in the Text, as if he would tell them of a Duty that none disputed against God has made you rational Creatutes, wil<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> you deny him reasonable Service?</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is your only Duty; you have bu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> this one thing to mind, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Its a most comely, lovely, useful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Duty, how does it sweeten all w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> do? and fills as with marrow and sweet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ness when we can but get up to it.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:204795:40"/>6. Its a universal Duty, and that both, (1.) As to all Men, none to be excused. and (2.) All of and in Man is to be improved this way, his Soul, Body, Spirit, Heart, Lip, Life. (3.) At all times, both in Life and Death, <hi>John</hi> 21.19. <hi>This he spake signifying by what death he should glorifie God.</hi> (4) In all places and companies, and upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, in all states and stations, prosperity, adversity, yea you are to glorifie him in the very Fires, and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. <hi>you are to do it in all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. This is a perpetual everlasting Duty: its never out of date in time, nor in Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; see <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15. <hi>Continually</hi> you are to praise him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="motive">
               <head>
                  <hi>Motive,</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>It is the peremptory command of the great God; and this well follows the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. This tells you why its your absolute Duty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> because God hath enjoyned it, and this is reason sufficient in any case. Its enough to stop all mouthes but those that have a mind to fight against God; (which you would be loth to do with your Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:204795:41"/> for their reasonable Edicts) he is wiser and stronger than you. And this is also good in it self, therefore commanded; some things are good because commanded, as keeping the Sabbath on such a day of the Week and not another, the manner of the Administrations of Sacraments, with many other things; these are good because he hath commanded them, but this is good in it self, and he hath also seriously commanded it, his very heart is in it, and he expects it at your hands.</p>
               <p>And he also commands it <hi>frequently,</hi> and such commands are especially to be noted, that are so inculcated; this is not only in the Text, but is the great scope of all the Scriptures which would be too tedious to show, and the other Motives will sufficiently prove. Sometimes he speaks of this as a King commanding it, sometimes as a Judge reproving the neglect of it, sometimes as a Friend intreating of you to do it, this often repeating of it denotes,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The weightiness of the matter, and</p>
               <p n="2">2. It also denotes his great concernedness
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:204795:41"/> in it. If a great King should thus often command a thing you would take notice of it, and you will see this often repeated if you do but look over the Scriptures men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned under the three first Heads.</p>
               <p>And I tell you it is his peremptory Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, so that he will abate nothing of it; he hath declared it (and there is no disanul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it) he will be glorified by you, or upon you to your utter ruine. Do not think it hard, for its a reasonable Duty, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.13. <hi>they are right Statutes and good Laws,</hi> Hos. 14. last <hi>All the wayes of the Lord are right: I</hi> say as <hi>Acts</hi> 4 19. <hi>Whether are you to obey God, or the Devil, world and Flesh? judge yee.</hi> This is a right command <hi>because it is your life, Deut.</hi> 32.46, 47. <hi>John</hi> 12. <hi>last</hi> what an excellent Text is that! he does not only say <hi>the Promise, but the Commandment is Life everlasting.</hi> And <hi>I know it</hi> (says Christ) denoting the certainty of it. May not God put that question to your Consciences, <hi>Prov</hi> 22.20. <hi>Have not I spoken to thee excellent things in Counsel and Knowledg? what could you say against it?</hi> its the most excellent command in the World, and if you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:204795:42"/> of it, your sin is the greater that you neglect it. The Spirit speaks <hi>expresly</hi> not <hi>implicitly</hi> in this thing, <hi>and shall not the wrath of this King be as the roaring of a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to you Amos.</hi> 3.6 <hi>Shall a Trumpet be blown in the City and the people not be afraid?</hi> I may say here as in <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.22. <hi>the Kings command is urgent:</hi> and though you think it hard, yet the Saints have loved such commands and embraced them. I'll only instance in <hi>David,</hi> Psalm 119:11. <hi>he would hide them, he loved them,</hi> ver: 127: <hi>and delighted in them,</hi> ver: 47: <hi>and longed for them,</hi> ver: 131. <hi>and would not forget them,</hi> ver: 176: <hi>but do them▪</hi> ver. 166:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="motive">
               <head>
                  <hi>Motive,</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>Our Creation, Redemption and Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by the sacred Trinity have reference to this very thing. You know the works of God are either essential, <hi>(viz)</hi> those that are common to the whole Trinity, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal which are proper to each Person, and both these are either as to external or intern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Objects. The internal are those that have no reference to any Object without God,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:204795:42"/> as the generation of the Son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal have reference to some Object without the Trinity, as <hi>Predestination, Creation,</hi> &amp;c: and that's a Rule here, that one and the same external work (in a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent consideration) is both essential and personal, as <hi>Creation, Redemption and Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> they are essential works of the whole Trinity, and yet in another respect are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal: and hence the Father being the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Trinity, is said <hi>to Create,</hi> and the Son taking our nature, is said <hi>to Redeem,</hi> the Holy Ghost proceeding from both, is said <hi>to make Application of all this to us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three Branches in this Motive.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our Creation was to Glorifie God; <hi>We were not made to Eat and to Drink,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but to glorifie God,</hi> (as the first answer in your Catechism shews) he made you to Work and Labour, not to play; <hi>to give all Diligence,</hi> &amp;c. You should ask your selves seriously, have I answered the great end of my Creation? A man had better lose his Life than the End of his Living. He made
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:204795:43"/> you for this End, Isa 43.7. <hi>I have Created him for my [glory] I have formed him, yea, I have made him.</hi> He made you to be <hi>Fact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors for him,</hi> not to <hi>Set up for your selves.</hi> And he made you at first after his own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, that you might with ease glorifie him: But it may be said of too many, as in Hos. 10.1. <hi>They bring forth Fruits to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Eph.</hi> 2.10. <hi>You are Created in Christ Jesus unto good works, and Psal.</hi> 102.8. as if he should say, they shall be to my glory, Rev. 4. last. <hi>For thy pleasure they are and were Created,</hi> that we should be to his wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Isa. 60.21. <hi>The work of my Hand, that I may be glorified.</hi> It is a dreadful thing to be made in vain. Gen. 6.6. <hi>It Repented God that he had made man;</hi> may not God (if I may say so with Reverence after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men) <hi>Repent</hi> that he made your <hi>Tongues</hi> that Swear, and Lye, and Talk vainly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Your <hi>Feet</hi> that lead you into wicked Company and to wicked Actions? <hi>&amp;c. He Repented that he made</hi> Saul <hi>King,</hi> in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.35. so he may of many of us, he <hi>Repents</hi> he has made us, and made us men, honourable in any respect or degree. May
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:204795:43"/> he not say to us, as Matth. 20.6. <hi>why stand you here all the day Idle?</hi> why did God make you different from Beasts? giving you Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, and Language? but that you should glorifie him? this is the fruit he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects from you, <hi>your Tongues should be your glory, as it was</hi> Davids, Psal. 16.9. Psal. 30. last.</p>
               <p>The second Branch, Your Redemption by Christ was for this end, all that he did, and suffered for you, was for this very one End. He has bought you, both Soul &amp; body for this, 1 Cor. 6. last. <hi>Ye are bought with a price therefore glorifie God in your Body, and in your Spirit, which are his</hi> You should do it, both in Soul and Body, Rom. 15.6. Titus 2.14. <hi>Who gave himself for us, to Redeem us from all iniquity.</hi> In Creation God gave you <hi>your selves,</hi> but in Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he gives you <hi>Christ,</hi> which is much more, and he Redeems from Sin, and that is it only that stands in the way of Gods Glory. Hence he that Redeems is called, <hi>The Holy One,</hi> Isa. 41.14. we are said to be <hi>Redeemed to God, Rev.</hi> 5.9. <hi>and from all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Psal.</hi> 130. <hi>last.</hi> as well as from Hell
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:204795:44"/>
                  <hi>And Christ died for you, that you might Live. unto God.</hi> 2 Cor 5.15. It is a blemish to Christ when you do not live to God, and yet profess to be Redeemed by him. <hi>Let the Redeemed of the Lord give him praise,</hi> Psal. 107.1, 2. Luke 1 54, 75. <hi>He hath Redeemed us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That we should serve him in Holiness and Righteousness all the days of our Life,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <hi>He bare our Sins</hi> for this.</p>
               <p>The Third Branch. Our Sanctification by the Holy Ghost is for this End. He is called the Holy Spirit, not only <hi>Formalitér sed Effectivé,</hi> he is not only Holy himself infinitely, but his work is to make you ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And shall God (as I may with Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence say) foul his fingers with you to make you of Clay? Shall the Son take Flesh, and Dye to Redeem you? and the Holy Ghost make it his work to apply all this to you? and will you not glorifie God? It is the work of the Holy Ghost to sanctifie you, and if you be not sanctified, you cannot glorifie God, and he is grieved when you oppose him in his sanctifying work, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse, or neglect to glorifie God. That it is his work, see 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. and that Conversion
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:204795:44"/> and Sanctification glorifie God, see 1 Pet. 2.5.9. you are said by these <hi>to shew forth the praises of him,</hi> &amp;c. And hence <hi>Grace</hi> is called <hi>Glory,</hi> 2 Cor 3. last.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Because it leads to glory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Because God is glorified by it, both by giving it, preserving it, and drawing it out into Exercise: They that have Gods holy Image on them are called his glory, Isa. 46. last. and the Church is called a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Church, Eph. 5.27.</p>
               <trailer>So much for the third Motive.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="motive">
               <p>The Fourth Motive. It is Gods chief End in all that he daily does, to glorifie himself. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. <hi>The Lord hath made all things for himself, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And not only Creation, but Preservation (which is a continued Creation) is for this End, this is,</p>
               <p n="1">1 The end of all Gods works, and all his Providences. If you Refuse to glorifie God you do as much as in you lies to make void all the Creation. Does God give you the Sun, to give you Light, to sin against
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:204795:45"/> him. The Creatures serve you, that you might serve him. What a wretched Creature is a Sinner! He would command every thing, and not be commanded by his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, but lifts up the heel against him. He does not give you his Creatures, that you should fulfil your Lusts with them, no doubt they shall rise up in Judgment against such as have not glorified God. It is observable, that God calls upon the irrational Creatures to praise him, in <hi>Psal.</hi> 148.3. <hi>To praise him is to glorifie him;</hi> This might reprove us, for not doing it. <hi>q. d;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have made man to glorifie me, but he does not, <hi>Come you and praise me.</hi> As he calls upon the Earth to hear, when men are deaf to him; but it especially means that we sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld when we behold the Curiosity, and Constancy of them, be Excited to praise God. Though they have no Tongues yet are said <hi>to declare his glory,</hi> Psal. 19.1. <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.3. though they cannot (as <hi>Plato</hi> thought) do it with understanding, yet with a dumb Eloquence they call on us to do it, and reprove our negligence; and they are the matter of our praise. Nay, all
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:204795:45"/> these things are upheld in their Beings, while waiting upon you, that you might honour God.</p>
               <p>All Gods Providential Acts are for this, <hi>viz.</hi> for his glory. As 1. When he preserves, protects, provides for his people, when he prevents their trouble, or delivers out of it, he has but this one end in all; when he works Miracles for them it is for his glory, John 2.11. Psal. 85.9. Temporal Salvation and Glory are put together, <hi>Salvation is nigh to them that fear him, that Glory may dwell in our Land.</hi> So Psal. 3.3. a Shield and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is put together, so Psal. 102.16. <hi>when God builds up Zion, he will appear in his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. And when he destroys his peoples E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, when he disappoints and frustrates them, this is for his glory, when he makes them fall into their own Pits. Read Exod. 14.17. to the twentieth verse and so on, you have the proof of this; and Numb. 14.13, to 21. <hi>Moses</hi> pleads with God, and in the conclusion is heard, and says God, <hi>All the Earth shall be filled with my Glory.</hi> That is, with the glory
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:204795:46"/> of his wisdom in frustrating them, of his power in Crushing them, and his Justice in being Revenged of them, and his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to his people and his Truth both as to his Promises and Threatnings.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Gods daily pardoning, supporting, strengthning, Counselling, Comforting, and giving greater degrees of Grace to his people; yea his very Afflicting of them, are all for this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd; and his hearing of their Prayers, affording his Presence in his Ordinances, all is for his Glory. Exo. 32.18. His Goodness is his glory, and he cannot put forth a greater act of glory, than in pardoning of Sin, <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.2, 3. last clause of it, 1 Kings 3.11. There was an extraordinary Appearance of Gods Presence, and that is his glory. All these are called his glory, as formerly you have heard in the first Explaining of the Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</p>
               <p>Gods Holiness lies in a <hi>willing</hi> of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as his ultimate end, and our holiness lies in making it our last End in every thing, and <hi>willing</hi> of other things in subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to it; even the meanest Believer in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:204795:46"/> this sence lives the life of God, <hi>from him, and unto him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They have all their grace, peace, strength, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from God, and all they do, is with a design to glorifie God in it.</p>
               <p>There is in every mercy two things; Comfort, and Glory; the Comfort he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows us to take, but the glory he will have himself, and good reason he should.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="motive">
               <p>The Fifth Motive. All that God hath done from Eternity, and all that he will do to Eternity, are for his glory: Why should not you then glorifie him in time? this was it that God was doing from Eternity, he was delighting himself, in himself, and designing his own glory.</p>
               <p>Two Branches here.</p>
               <p>The First Branch. All that he has done from Eternity, those Eternal Purposes of God, which Relate to the Creature (to wit) Election and praeterition.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Election, in his chusing some here, some there as he pleases, He only designs his glory in all; nothing out of himself
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:204795:47"/> moves him, he will chuse because he will, only for the glory of his Grace; <hi>and this is it that affords Rivers of Oyl, to feed the Flames of Eternal Extasies among the Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Eph.</hi> 1.6, 12, 14. You see it is for his Glory. Hence his <hi>mercy</hi> is called his <hi>glory, Eph.</hi> 3.16. <hi>The Riches of his Glory, and it is that we should be to the praise of the Glory of his Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Praeterition also, that is a good Rule in Divinity, <hi>that Damnation is not the end of praeterition,</hi> (or passing by of any) <hi>but the manifestation of the glory of Gods Justice.</hi> These things many stumble at, because Gods Word is a <hi>savour of Death to them, but it is for his glory, Rom.</hi> 9.22. It is <hi>to make his power known,</hi> as he did on <hi>Pharaoh, Exodus</hi> 14.4. <hi>Rom</hi> 9.17. It is not Gods pleasure in mens ruine, but his own glory he designs in all.</p>
               <p>The Catechism tells you, it is for his glory, That
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>His Decrees are an Eternal fore-ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that comes to pass.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>That the Cause of them is the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of his Will.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:204795:47"/>
                     <item>3. <hi>That the end is his own Glory.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I might also have mentioned the eternal Generation of the Son of God, which was hinted at before; this being an immanent act from Eternity, was for his Glory: hence the Apostle in this sence calls Christ <hi>the Glory of God,</hi> Heb. 1.3. yea, <hi>the brightness of his Glory:</hi> this he sayes when he is speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Son-ship in that Chapter.</p>
               <p>Also his giving Christ a Body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough done in time) was also for his <hi>Glory,</hi> John 1.14.</p>
               <p>The Second Branch of the Motive is, All that God will do to all Eternity is for his Glory.</p>
               <p>The salvation of his People for ever, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Glory sits upon the head of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and truth; his Saints shall be for ever with him, and ever be giving him the glory of it. They shall admire and adore him for ever; Heaven is the Land of Hallelujahs, we shall not then be as we are here, one day in a praising, admiring frame, and two or three dayes out of it: there is not one Soul in Heaven but <hi>Glorifies God</hi> as much
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:204795:48"/> as he would have it to do. They do their work well and God likes it as well. Heaven is called <hi>Glory,</hi> Luk. 24.26. Christ the Head is Glorified, and he will never leave praying, till he have all his Members with him, and the hopes of Heaven is called <hi>the hopes of Glory,</hi> Rom. 5.2. Heaven is called <hi>Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Because much of Gods Glory is to be seen there, that could not be seen here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Because it was created for his Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Because he will be there perfectly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eternally glorified, they shall begin betime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to do it, and shall hold on for ever,</hi> 2 Thess. 1.10. <hi>And now what a strong Motive is this to us all, to make it our business to Glorifye God: Consider here but these</hi> four things in it. <hi>that,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. All that God has done from first to last is for his Glory, stop here and think, why should not we do thus?</p>
               <p n="2">2. That God will glorifie his People to all Eternity. And is not this a sufficient Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to you to <hi>glorifie him now?</hi> Rom. 8.30. <hi>(Glorified)</hi> that is, <hi>He has adorned them with grace here, and will adorn them with Glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi> If you could be assured that you should within this month be glorified with him at what a rate would you live! and though
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:204795:48"/> you walk in darkness, and see no light, yet its your duty to <hi>glorifie God;</hi> and a good Child will love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd serve his Father, though he have no Inheritance to give him. A spirit of Adoption lies much in this, that the Soul would <hi>glorifie God,</hi> though it be not sure that God will glorifie it. But ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities? if you have the least degree of probability, there is infinite reason you should <hi>glorifie him.</hi> Have you closed with the call of the Gospel? are you willing to go with Christ? then you are as <hi>good as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified.</hi> God will make <hi>you glorious,</hi> he will so deck you with Glory, that you shall love your selves for Gods likeness on you. But <hi>I</hi> conclude you never expect to be <hi>Glorified</hi> by God, if you make it not your business <hi>to glorifie him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. You have but a little time <hi>to glorifie God</hi> in, after that manner that you do it here. Indeed in Heaven you <hi>shall glorifie</hi> him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, but not after such a manner in all respects as you do it here, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>By Faith,</hi> as it glorifies God in times of temptations, Desertions, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 4.20.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:204795:49"/> O think, why should not <hi>I</hi> glorifie God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my temptations, <hi>&amp;c. I</hi> have but a little time to do it in.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>By Repentance,</hi> living a life of <hi>Godly sorrow</hi> confessing Sin, lying low before God, <hi>Josh.</hi> 7.19. how should you now be looking back upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat has been amiss, and mourn! for Repentance is out of date in Heaven.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By standing up for the cause and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of Christ in the World, and in the places where you live.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When you can do no more, you should be willing to suffer for Christ: there is no Martyrdome in Heaven, and God is glorified by this, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14, 16. this was an honour that the holy Angels were never capable of, this Father <hi>Latimer</hi> very much desired and had at last.</p>
               <p n="5">5. You should do it by an exemplary conversation, in the midst of a crooked and perverse generation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. this you may see more of under the Explication how <hi>you are to glorifie God in your deportment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Consider also, that your glorifying God now, will fit you the more for it when you come to do it in Heaven. Begin Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:204795:49"/> upon Earth; settle to your work now, the more you glorifie God now, the more you will do it then, and the more you will be glorified also: for none doubts but there are degrees of Glory, and Grace is Glory begun. I do not here put you upon the thought of meriting, for there is infinite dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion between the work and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; that glory that shall be revealed in you infinitely out-does your endeavours and attainments: however you should in a way of Love and Gratitude desire to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that God now, that will so glorifie you, and by using your selves to it, you would be Masters of your Trade (as we use to say of some that have served an Apprenticeship to a Trade.) That makes Religion so hard, you accustome your selves to it so little. If God should take up unsanctified persons to Heaven, they would not be fit for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment there; what haters of God spend their Eternity in praising him! that's not likely, they are weary of holy exercises now, how should they rub out endless Eternity in such work!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So much for the fifth great Motive.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="motive">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:204795:50"/>
               <head>Motive, <hi>6.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Lord Jesus Christ began betimes to glorifie his Father, and held on so to do till the very last moment that he drew breath in this World. Here you may look back to what was said in the former part of the Discourse, about <hi>a Christ-like Deportment;</hi> but I may add by way of <hi>Motive</hi> more to what was there said. He did thus, and shall not the same mind be in you that was in him? if Christ be not your <hi>principle</hi> and <hi>patern,</hi> he will not be your <hi>price,</hi> you ought to walk as he walked, to be daily <hi>Looking</hi> unto him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. as a man that's drawing a Picture, or a School-boy at his Copy. And he grew in Grace betimes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.49. and made it his business to glorifie God, and you may see he held on in so doing, by <hi>John</hi> 17.4, 5. <hi>I have glorified thee on Earth, I have fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished the work thou gavest me to do, now O Father glorifie thou me,</hi> &amp;c. this confirms what was said before, <hi>that they that glorifie God shall be glorified by him.</hi> It would be a blessed thing to be able to say at death, as
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:204795:50"/>
                  <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did, <hi>Isai.</hi> 38.3. and as <hi>Paul</hi> did, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finished my course, I have kept the Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And Christ did all along glorifie God, though he found it costly work yet he fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished it, he was concerned for his Fathers Glory, <hi>Father glorifie thy Name,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 12.27, 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.31. <hi>God is glorified in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not but that Christ <hi>as God</hi> is as much an Object of honour as the Father; but we now speak of him as he is a Mediator, and so subject to the Father; and his Fathers mind and will, <hi>was his meat and drink,</hi> John 4.34. <hi>and his only business,</hi> John 6.38. <hi>he came not to do his own will, but the will of him that sent him.</hi> And he tells us, <hi>the zeal of Gods House had eaten him up;</hi> and at death sayes, <hi>Lord, not my will but thy will be done,</hi> O what an excellent Example is this! and what a Motive might it be unto us!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="motive">
               <head>Motive, <hi>7.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Gods Glory is the most weighty and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious thing in Heaven and Earth: and will you rob him of that? O give him his glory
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:204795:51"/> then, for it is the most dangerous thing in the World to rob him of it, he has said <hi>He will not give it to another,</hi> Isai. 42.8. and its repeated again in <hi>Isai.</hi> 48.11. this is the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Fruit, he will have none to finger it, he has but this one thing incomparably dear to him, its all he aims at, all he is concerned for; and if you have not glorified him, you have done nothing in the World to any purpose: God sayes to us all as he did to Christ, <hi>John</hi> 12.28. <hi>I have both glorified my Name, and will do it again:</hi> I will have every body to do it, or neglect it at their utmost peril. Sometimes <hi>his glory</hi> is said in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be <hi>great, exceeding great, higher than the Heavens, and its said to fill all the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is more worth than your Souls, and Salvation. Who or what are we? that God should mind our Salvation, and bring us to glory by Christs Death? who can think he should Dye ultimately for us?</p>
               <p>Though our Salvation was the immediate and Proxime End of his Death, it was Gods glory that was the ultimate end of his Death. He dyed not ultimately to glorifie himself, Heb. 5.5. <hi>It was his Fathers Will;</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:204795:51"/> he did not thrust himself upon it. Althô it is true, his Exaltation came after his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, yet this was not his ultimate end. Much less then was your Salvation his ultimate end, though at the same time he shewed the highest Love, both to God and you, that could be.</p>
               <p>The Glory of God is infinitely better than our Salvation; so that if Gods Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour should have been impaired, Justice vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olated, and his Truth broken, who durst have been seen in it? But it is so ordered by infinite Wisdom, that God is no loser by it, but all his Attributes are eminently glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by the death of Christ, never such an instance of Grace and Mercy, as in the death of Christ; you have many instances of his Mercy, in <hi>Psal.</hi> 136. but no such an instance as this. And this makes the sin of the Devils so great, that in opposing of your Salvation, they oppose the glory of God, by the death of Christ, for God in infinite grace has joined his Glory and our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both together: So that it is matter of great comfort, that when Christ is said to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:204795:52"/> glorifie God in Dying, it is meant his grace and mercy is glorified by your Redemption, and his glory and your good, are never to be separated. So that God is a gainer by this way of Salvation, as well as you, his Justice not only satisfied, but Grace exalted by it. And as it glorifies the true Grace, so also the wisdom of God <hi>Solomons Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was admired in giving judgment between the two Harlots.</hi> We have a Story in Hist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory, <hi>Of a great Emperour that made a Law, That every Adulterer should have his Eyes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out; and his own Son being found guilty, he had no other way to save the honour of his Justice, and yet to save his Sons Eyes; but caused one of his Sons Eyes, and one of his own to be Bored out.</hi> This Story has been much admired, but we have infinitely more cause to admire the Wisdom of God in the death of Christ. And as it glorifies his Grace and Wisdom, so also his Justice; it is both a merciful Justice, and a just Mercy. So also his power: Christ is called both the Wisdom and Power of God in this Respect. Thus God is glorified by the death of Christ, and this was his ultimate end in dying.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:204795:52"/>
               <p>For he did not glorifie God that we might be saved, but dyed to save us, that God might be glorified. All the Souls in the world are nothing compared with the glory of God; better we all should perish, than God should lose his Glory; though one Soul would weigh down ten thousand Worlds of other things. Gods glory is a greater good than your Salvation; for your Salvation is but as the Medium, his glory is the <hi>Ʋltimus finis.</hi> His Glory must needs be of more worth than your Salvation, for that is only the good of a Creature, his glory is like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. However, these are not to be parted, for God hath joined them, he has commanded you to seek his glory, and also Immortality and Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>And now from this you may infer two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How should Christians walk that are trusted with such a weighty thing, as the glory of God! how very provoking are the sins of Professors, and their scandalous Lives? You should walk blamelesly, <hi>and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:204795:53"/> depart from iniquity, for Gods name is upon you,</hi> and you should be more tender of the Name of God, than of your own names.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moses</hi> was Eminent, for that he was more concerned for Gods glory than his own. You should carry so, as to stop all mouths, (at least when they come to dye, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12.) James 2.7. Rom. 2.23, 24. <hi>The wickedness of a Servant reproacheth his Mast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. And do not you pretend to be Gods Servants</hi> &amp; <hi>Children? Salvian</hi> used to write much against the bad Lives of the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and told them, that the Heathen might well say, <hi>Christiani sancté vixissent, si Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us sancta Docuisset.</hi> Christians would have Lived better, if Christ had taught them better. Oh, wipe off this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach by your blameless Lives. Gods glory is his <hi>Spouse,</hi> he is very jealous as to this, <hi>Joseph had the charge of all</hi> Potiphars <hi>House except his Wife.</hi> But God has trusted you with the best thing he has in the world, <hi>viz.</hi> his glory, and then how tender and careful should you be of it.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:204795:53"/>2. Again we may infer this, That if our Salvation be to be Referr'd to the glory of God, then much more all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, Health, Honour, Parts, and Wealth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What have you all for, but to glorifie God? The <hi>End</hi> is beyond the <hi>Means,</hi> you are to account it so, and to look beyond <hi>them,</hi> and desire no more of <hi>them,</hi> than leads unto the End. As an Old Saying, <hi>Media movent Bonitate Finis. The Means moves through the goodness of the End.</hi> You do not desire all the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Fountain, but as much as will quench your Thirst, nor all the Cloth in the world, but what is needful to cover you. So here you ought to desire these things only with Reference to the glory of God.</p>
               <p>So much for the seventh Motive.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="motive">
               <head>
                  <hi>Motive</hi> 8.</head>
               <p>If you will not glorifie God, he will be glorified upon you. Put him not to strain for his own. If you will not sanctifie him,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:204795:54"/> he will sanctifie himself; if you do not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify him intentionally, he will be glorified eventually, if not actually, he will be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified passively, if you bear not witness to his Holinefs, He will do it himself by his Judgments. (as one well saith) There is not one in a Congregation, but the Holy God is sanctified by him, or else upon him, by Spiritual Plagues and Judgments, which are the worst, and alwayes certain, though not alwayes visible. We may plainly see in that instance of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu, (though the Eldest Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of a good man, and in the Priests Office.)</hi> That Gods glory is dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to him than mens Lives, Lev. 10.3. <hi>God would not bear with them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another instance of this, is <hi>Herod;</hi> (though a very great man) God would not bear with him, Acts 12.23. You have his death, and the manner of it, <hi>he was smitten, and that immediately, by the Minist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Angels, and mortally, he gave up the Ghost, and shamefully, Eaten of Worms, or Lice, as his Grand-father</hi> Herod <hi>was before;</hi> and then you have the Reasons of it, <hi>He
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:204795:54"/> gave not God the glory, being unjust, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable therein.</hi> This might seem but a small thing, but God took it very ill. The Apostles did otherwise, Acts 14.13, 14. <hi>When the people would have done Sacrifice to them, they ran in amongst them,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Peter when Cornelius fell down at his Feet,</hi> Acts 10.26. <hi>bids him stand up,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I have heard of a man, that Lived a very Atheistical Life, who was in a sad case when he came to Dye, crying out, if there be a God, I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you see God will have his glory, if you will not give it him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="motive">
               <head>
                  <hi>Motive</hi> 9.</head>
               <p>God is infinitely worthy of it. Therefore <hi>I</hi> beg it of you: if he do not deserve it at your hands, i'le give you leave to deny me. It is gross Idolatry to give it any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And this is the Reason of the last Motive. He may well take it ill, when you do not give it him, seeing he is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:204795:55"/> most worthy, altogether, only and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely Worthy, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4. <hi>last. Thou art wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy O Lord, of Glory, praise, &amp;c.</hi> God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds all things in glory, <hi>Heaven &amp; Earth is full of his Glory;</hi> and he should have it all. God deserves the glory on a double account.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. He is his own glory.</item>
                  <item>2. He is your glory also.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. God is his own glory, he is absolutely and independently so. Why should you not give God his own? Sometimes Riches are called Glory in Scripture, and outward Honour, Learning, Victory, a good Name, Authority, Prosperity, and Grace is called Glory: but all these are but derivative, and none have all of these; but God is his own glory and he needs none to add to him. Hence he is called <hi>Glorious,</hi> Exod. 15 11. and he is so, not only in his Holiness, but in every thing else. Every thing in God is glorious; he is incomparably glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. And if he be so glorious in the world, <hi>The Sun, Moon, and Stars, declare his Glory,</hi> &amp;c. So glorious in his Church, in his Word, Works, and in his Saints, Psal. 45.13. <hi>The
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:204795:55"/> Spouse is all glorious within;</hi> in his Angels, his Sanctuary, Ministers, Gospel, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What is that God that hath ordered and Beautified all these, Psal. 66.2. You should then <hi>make his praise glorious;</hi> his Right-hand is called <hi>glorious, his power is glorious,</hi> Col. 1.11. he is so glorious, that he doth and can, without weakness, glory in himself. How many glorious descripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have you of God in Scripture! which <hi>I</hi> have opened upon other occasions, as in Isa. 40. and in Isa. 57.15. and in many more places, yet we cannot say his glorying is not good, <hi>for his glory is infinitely above all other glory,</hi> and it is <hi>his own.</hi> I am not able in the least to set him off to you, his back-parts are <hi>only</hi> seen in this World, <hi>you cannot see his face and live:</hi> if you knew him, you could not but fall in love with him He is called <hi>the God of Glory,</hi> and <hi>the Father of Glory,</hi> Eph. 1.17. Acts 7.2. there is a glory of God that is absolute, and none can conceive of, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.18, 22, 23. and he is called the <hi>Lord of Glory</hi> and <hi>King of Glory; Glory and Honour</hi> are said <hi>to be in his presence,</hi> &amp;c. thus he is his own Glory.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:204795:56"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Branch</hi> 2. He is your Glory also. He puts an honour upon you, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Margent,</hi> to them that believe he is <hi>the Honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am almost out of heart to speak to others, I would now speak to Christians, Christ is your Glory and Honour, <hi>Luk</hi> 2.32. just as a person of <hi>Honour</hi> Marrying a mean person makes her <hi>Honourable, Isai.</hi> 43 4. <hi>since thou wast precious in my sight, thou hast been honourable,</hi> &amp;c. and you find in Scripture, that the Saints <hi>have accounted God their glory, Psal.</hi> 3.3. and if you have any interest in God, you may say thus, so <hi>Psal</hi> 62.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> shall show you in five things how God is the <hi>Glory of his People</hi> and in what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects.</p>
               <p>And these things might all serve as Motives, to perswade you to Glorifie him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He is their Glory, in that he does not only permit them, and command them <hi>to Glorifie him,</hi> but is also pleased to account himself glorified by them.</p>
               <p>This is a piece of great condescention in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in him, who is infinitely above the Admirations and Services of the Holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:204795:56"/> themselves, (and therefore he is said to <hi>humble himself,</hi> to behold things done in Heaven,) that he should account himself, <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by you,</hi> and that he should take any thing well at your hands; he not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it, but commends it, <hi>Psal.</hi> 50 <hi>ult.</hi> That he should account you make him glorious by your right conceptions of him, and your Gospel conversations; this is your Glory, and might be a strong Motive to you. That he should be found of you, and suffer you to come so near him, and to stand in his Courts, is your honour, but that he should be pleased to account himself glorified by you is more.</p>
               <p>He is said to be glorified on your part, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14. and <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.8. <hi>he takes pleasure in it,</hi> as if he should say, <hi>I take it well, I account my self glorified by you.</hi> And old Divine expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses himself thus, <hi>that when any man glorifies God, he is accounted by God to make him glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and to give him as it were a new</hi> Being, (though this is soberly to be understood.)</p>
               <p>No doubt when any person does eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>Glorifie God,</hi> he sets him off as it were <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ew</hi> before others. And that God should
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:204795:57"/> account thus of it, is a very <hi>great Honour.</hi> You read of the blinde and lame, the Lepers and Centurion, and the Gentiles, that they <hi>glorified God,</hi> and he takes notice of all these, as I might give Scriptures for them all: he took it well from them; <hi>O this is your glory, when God accepts of you in what you do.</hi> The Saints in the worst of conditions may live upon their present acceptance and their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture recompence.</p>
               <p n="2">2 He puts a great <hi>glory</hi> upon his People, in that he hath, he daily doth, and will mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie them to all Eternity.</p>
               <p n="1">1 He not only hath magnified man (as before) in Creation, Redemption, &amp;c. in Creation making him but little lower than the Angels, and putting all things under his feet, that if he had stood all the Creatures should have been subject to him, having furnished the World plentifully and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficently for him, before he came into it, this was a <hi>great Honour,</hi> but he has honoured his People much more by Redemption, in that when you had sold your selves to Satan to your sins, and to the justice of God, he should be at such cost <hi>to Redeem you,</hi> is not this
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:204795:57"/> an honour? Would it not be an honour for a Prince to give many thousand pounds to redeem a poor Slave out of <hi>Turkey?</hi> how may you admire God then, who has put such an honour upon you in Redemption, and that by his own Son too, and by his precious blood! this indeed is <hi>an honour,</hi> and might be a great Motive to glorifie him.</p>
               <p>And he has also put an honour upon you in your conversion to him, whereby the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God is renewed in you, and you are made partakers of the Divine Nature, and come to live the life of God, all which is a mighty glory to you.</p>
               <p>And if God be thus your glory and have so magnified you; why should not you glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him?</p>
               <p n="2">2. He daily doth magnifie and put Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our upon his People, in that he preserves them even by a Guard of Angels, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. admits them to communion with him, that at any time he smiles on them, accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and embraceth them, counselling sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting, supplying them as they need; and that also he should afflict them rather than
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:204795:58"/> lose them, (for he loves them too well to let them live in any sin uncorrected) all this is their honour; thus God is their glory. Its an honour to you that so glorious a God should contend with you by affliction, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.14. and more, that he should cause it to work for you an eternal weight of glory, and bring you to glory at last: thus he puts a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry upon his People both in life and at death.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He will glorifie them to all Eternity, this I but name, it has been hinted at before: but God is both your glory in life, at death, and after death? he might have forbidden you to glorifie him, and then you had been miserable: O glorifie him then to your utmost.</p>
               <p n="3">3 He is your glory, in that he hath put you into so near a Relation to himself, and put himself into so near a Relation unto you: he calls himself <hi>your Father, your Husband, your God, your Shepherd, (I</hi> might bring Scriptures for all these) and your Saviour, yea your <hi>own God.</hi> Can you do too much for your Father, your heavenly Father? if you be true Christians God is really your
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:204795:58"/> Father. What a great thing did <hi>David</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it to be Son in Law to a King? but happy are they <hi>whose God is the Lord.</hi> This is the highest <hi>Honour</hi> that can be, and whilst others boast of this and that, <hi>you may make your boast of God for ever▪</hi> Glory in your Knowledge of him, and of your interest in him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.11. in the Greek, <hi>But we Boast in God, through Jesus Christ. I</hi> may say as <hi>Esth.</hi> 6.11. <hi>You are such as this King delighteth to Honour:</hi> why then should you not <hi>honour</hi> him, with all you are, have, and can do?</p>
               <p>Its observable how many Names God gives to his People in Scripture, which sets forth this thing, and you should answer your Names. Are you called <hi>the Sons of God,</hi> and will you not honour your Father? Mal. 1.6. you are called <hi>Vessels,</hi> and are you leaking Vessels? Can you hold no glory for God 2 Tim. 2.20, 21. when a man makes a Vessel he has it for some use or other. Who made you <hi>Vessels of Honour?</hi> and <hi>why did free Grace chuse you?</hi> but many are Vessels in whom there is no <hi>pleasure, Jer</hi> 22.28. not <hi>meet for their Masters use.</hi> You might have been suffered to have been Vessels of wrath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.21. it was Grace
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:204795:59"/> that made you otherwise: you are also cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Members of Christ,</hi> and <hi>will you not honour your Head? will you rise up in rebellion against your Head?</hi> nay, you are called <hi>his Flesh, and his Bones,</hi> Eph. 5.30. and <hi>will you dishonour your Head?</hi> 1 Cor. 11.4.</p>
               <p>Are you not called Temples of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost; and will you not honour God? <hi>In his Temple should every one speak of his glory. Ps.</hi> 29 9. Much of glory was in the Temple, and God was Glorified and Worshiped in his Temple. If you be Gods House, then he dwells in you, and by so doing he hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours you; Will you not glorifie the Master of the House? 1 Cor. 3.16. <hi>What, know you not that you are the Temple of God? And that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?</hi> 1 Cor. 6.19, 20. <hi>Wherefore glorifie God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And you are called the people of his <hi>Choice, his chosen Generation,</hi> and what was it for? see 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5, 9 &amp; in <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5. <hi>his Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Treasure. Acts</hi> 9.15. <hi>Chosen Vessels.</hi> And will you not glorifie him?</p>
               <p>You are called the <hi>Heirs of Glory,</hi> and ere long you must <hi>inherit glory,</hi> and will you not glorifie him? Heb. 1. <hi>last. Heirs
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:204795:59"/> of Salvation, Heb.</hi> 6.17. <hi>called the Heirs of promise;</hi> How should such honour God!</p>
               <p n="4">4. He is your g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> in that he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested you with many great priviledges that are your glory. As his affording of you many means of grace, seasons and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of glorifying him, planting you in his Vineyard. (I wish you understood your mercy in this) <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.3. shall God thus honour you? and will you not honour him? This very thing hath honoured our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons more than any part of the world, the greatest part of the world are not thus hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oured. He has made you <hi>Trees of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness:</hi> Your great Clusters of sin, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity should fall off; and <hi>you should be La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with fruits of Righteousness to his Glory. Phil.</hi> 1.11. But O what Clusters of wrath do some bring forth! What a lovely thing would it be for you to bring forth Clusters of Faith and Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he hath not dealt with other Nations as by us, Psal. 147. last. Has he not <hi>Created a Defence upon your glory? Isa</hi> 4.5. Your good fruit <hi>would glorifie your Father and Christs Father, John</hi> 15.8. <hi>John</hi> 20.17. Our Sabbaths are our glory, <hi>Isai.</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:204795:60"/> 58.13. and your Ministers are to be hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oured for their works sake, nay, they are called the glory of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> (though accounted the off-scouring of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ngs)</hi> 2 Cor 8.23. and they are your honour, <hi>for whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>all are yours; they are the gift of Christ,</hi> and it is said, <hi>no man takes this honour unto himself, but he that is called,</hi> &amp;c. It is a blessed thing when Gods Word <hi>Runs</hi> and is <hi>Glorified.</hi> But it may be our glory is departing, then call your Comforts <hi>Jchabod,</hi> as she in 1 Sam. 4.21, 22.</p>
               <p n="5">5. God has put a mighty glory upon you in that he does in so many words call and account you his glory, <hi>Isa.</hi> 46. <hi>last. Israel my glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed it is very much he should be <hi>your glory,</hi> but that you should be <hi>his glory</hi> is much more, <hi>Isa.</hi> 60.7. <hi>You are the joy and Crown of Christ,</hi> which is more than to be <hi>Pauls joy and Crown,</hi> Phil. 4.1. Isa. 62.3. <hi>Thou shalt be a Crown of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a Royal Diadem in the hand of thy God.</hi> So that <hi>I</hi> may say <hi>glorious</hi> things are said of you through free grace, and will you not glorifie God?</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:204795:60"/>
               <p>So much for the ninth great Motive.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="motive">
               <head>
                  <hi>Motive</hi> 10.</head>
               <p>The greatest part of men in the world do downright dishonour God: and you your selves have but very little glorified him hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto. And shall God have no glory in the world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and this well follows the last; it aggravates your doing so little this way if God be your glory.</p>
               <p>Two Branches here.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The greatest part of mankind do downright dishonour him; they generally provoke the Eyes of his glory, they know no shame, they hide it not, but instead of glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, they <hi>turn his glory into shame,</hi> Psal. 4.2. yea, they glory in their shame. It was an old complaint in <hi>Rom.</hi> 3 23. and those sins that are most common amongst us, <hi>I</hi> could show you how they are said to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour God. But now when others do so, let us grow more holy by it. Methinks
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:204795:61"/> the Name and glory of God cries out, Who will be on my side, Who? It hath few faithful Friends in the world, now turn to him, and glorifie him so much the more. Let him not have your <hi>blow</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Rest, <hi>nor</hi> let your helping hand be <hi>Imployed to</hi> thrust his <hi>glory out of</hi> the <hi>World. The whole world lies in wickedness there is none that does good, whole Volleys of Impieties are daily discharged against him.</hi> We may say of most, as Dan. 5.23. <hi>The God in whose hand is their breath, and whose are all their ways have they not glorified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be wondred at, Rev. 15.4. <hi>Who shall not fear thee, and glorifie thy name?</hi> All things but Devils and wicked men glorifie him, and they shall (though against their wills.) He may complain of the most of the world that they have Robbed him.</p>
               <p>The Second Branch.</p>
               <p>You have but very little glorifyed him your selves hitherto.</p>
               <p>Is it not time now to begin? Shame might help you a little here; grow the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:204795:61"/> this cold time. <hi>David</hi> did so, <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.126, 127. <hi>They have made void thy Law, Thorefore I love thy Commandments,</hi> &amp;c. but you have yet done little, how little in your Closets, Families, or the Church, have you done? how little have you been in praise, in Prayer? how little have others glorified God through you; how seldom have you been in thinking, speaking, Admiring, Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Commending of him to others? how little on week-days have you glorified him? and how little on Lords-Days? O now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin your Reformation, and lay your foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in deep Humiliation, lay your hand upon your mouth, and Resolve through Christ, that you will be more holy, and heavenly, useful, and prayerful, than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; be now more for serious godliness than ever. O it is high time to mend, and God expects it at your hands, see what he would have you be, Jer. 13.11. <hi>a praise and a name, and a glory to him.</hi> Do not refuse as they did there.</p>
               <p>But alas, the greatest part of the world may be reduced unto three Ranks.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Such that have done very little, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:204795:62"/> the abilities and opportunities they have had, they have Prayed, Repented, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and Lived little, that came late into the Vineyard, or have been Loyterers in it, or have gone back from his work, <hi>they have put their hands to the Plough, and look back.</hi> Some indeed <hi>é contrà</hi> have lived much in a little time. <hi>Abraham</hi> it is said, <hi>Dyed old and full of years,</hi> though he lived not so long as many others. But he was full of God, of Grace and Comfort.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Many that have done nothing at all, but only have lived to Eat and Drink, <hi>Buy and Sell,</hi> &amp;c. and so have only <hi>Cumbred the Ground;</hi> it is said in <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. such and such they lived so many years and they dyed, and nothing set down Remarkable in their Lives. Thus it is with very many.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There are many that have done worse than nothing, that live in Rebellion, and are bad Examples, Corrupting all about them; that in stead of living to God, live to themselves, and the World, yea to the Devil.</p>
               <p>And this should Excite us the more to glorifie God, to Repair the loss of his
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:204795:62"/> Glory what in us lies.</p>
               <p>So much for the Tenth Motive.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="motive">
               <head>Motive <hi>11</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This hath ever been the Language of all true Converts, at the very first; <hi>What shall we do to glorifie God?</hi> bewailing bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly the former neglect of this. And if this be not the care and business of your Lives, (if there be a Living God) your state is naught, though you may reform, and do much, you are yet unconverted. Acts 13.48. When the Gentiles begin righty to apprehend of God, they then glorifie him; thus do you, and that both in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self and people, and every thing else. And see this, the Day will come when Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters shall not lose their Love upon any Hypocrite, they shall know who have glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified God, and who have not. See the Language of that Heavenly Host, in <hi>Luke</hi> 2.14. <hi>Glory be to God in the Highest,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> that great Convert concludes some of his Epistles with <hi>Glory to God.</hi> O see that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:204795:63"/> you be such as thus do, else you are not Converted. And to <hi>come near</hi> the Kingdom of Heaven and not <hi>get into it,</hi> will make your Condemnation the greater.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="motive">
               <head>The Twelfth Motive.</head>
               <p>This would be the only way to glorifie Jesus Christ your Saviour, and to be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with him for ever.</p>
               <p>It is meet that you should glorifie him, that spent his breath, and his precious blood for you. Oh who would not live to the Glory of such a Redeemer! That day is lost that is not spent (in part at least) in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, and Admiring of Jesus Christ; if you would glorifie Christ, then glorifie God 2 Thes. 1. last. It is the best prayer in the world next to the prayer of Christ, <hi>That the Name of our Lord Jesus Christ may be glorified in you,</hi> &amp;c And there is great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son we should glorifie Christ, for God the Father has glorified him: He has not only received him to Glory, and set him at his own Right-hand, but he also glorifies him in that he will do nothing without him,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:204795:63"/>
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Thou wentest down with thine An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed.</hi> He directs us alwayes to go to him under all our difficulties, and hath <hi>committed all power to him,</hi> and has <hi>given him a Name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove every name.</hi> Some have been called <hi>Jesus,</hi> some have been called <hi>Christ,</hi> but none besides himself called <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> God is well pleased when you glorifie Christ, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.10. and the Holy Ghost glorifies Christ, <hi>John.</hi> 16.14. I need not to tell you Christ is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, for the Scriptures are full of that. Christ is most glorious When most contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, <hi>Isai.</hi> 53.2. Now if you would glorifie Jesus Christ, you must glorifie God by chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing him for your happiness and portion, and daily pursue your choice. Nothing more glorifies Christ than conformity to him; we honour him most when we do as he did, and his Life was a continual living to God (as before) <hi>John</hi> 8.29. And you are also to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie Christ at your death, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.20. and this you do when you die believingly, and at Christs Command, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.5. witnessing to the Truth of Christ, <hi>John</hi> 21.19. and this is the way to be glorified with him, <hi>He that honours me I will honour,</hi> sayes God, and <hi>John</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:204795:64"/> 12, 26. <hi>he that serveth me, him will my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honour, and where I am there shall my servant be also.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="motive">
               <head>Motive, <hi>13.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>By Glorifying God much now, you lay a Foundation for your glorifying of him, <hi>upon Earth,</hi> even when <hi>you are in Heaven.</hi> No doubt God hath much glory here upon Earth, by means of his holy useful servants, when they have been long in eternal glory; and not only from holy Ministers, who have left converting Books behind, that have been much blessed to survivers, and whereby with <hi>Abel,</hi> they <hi>being dead yet speak:</hi> and holy Examples too, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. but also private Saints are concerned herein, to be laying in a stock to trade with for God when they are gone to glory. And thus many have done, and we ought to do, by good words, works, holy and exemplary lives, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations, Admonitions, Instructions and Consolations, by doing and suffering fo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Christ, &amp;c. Let me intreat you in the Name of Christ, to be laying in a rich stock of al<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:204795:64"/> these to leave with your Posterity, Friends and Families, nay all that ever had to do with you, that they may <hi>trade</hi> with it for the glory of God, and <hi>hand</hi> it down to them that shall come after them. O let us be writing good Copies every day for them that come after us, <hi>Nulla dies sine lineâ.</hi> That they may say so, and so, did my Father and Mother, Husband and Wife, &amp;c. walk, so did they behave themselves in Closet Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and in the Church of God; so did they perform Duties, hear Burthens, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press their Passions, and deny themselves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thus be, doing good after your Death. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4. Preach your own Funeral Ser-Sermons every day by living for Posterity, Nay the Motive is yet stronger (if that be true which some Divines have positively as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted) <hi>that the good you now do upon E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th does not only increase after your death, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so as that increaseth so your Glory will increase,</hi> say they: God will not only reward men according to their works, but according to the fruit of them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.10. so that if their holy Actions on Earth do fructifie after their Death, the fruits of them shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:204795:65"/> and follow them; <hi>Rev.</hi> 14 13. And so do the evil works of wicked men, as <hi>Jerob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hams</hi> did for above 300 years after his death, which made his Hell more hot. This is thought to be the Reason why <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves</hi> did desire his Brothers might avoid that place of <hi>Torment,</hi> because it would <hi>increase</hi> his <hi>own,</hi> for we cannot imagin natural affection, or the desire of the Salvation of others, to be in Hell. Nay it is said that the Glorified shall by their enlarged Crowns, and Additional glory, know the good they did here, and left behind them, doth fructify, which shall make them break forth into new Songs of Praise to God, and the Lamb, that helped them to sow that seed on Earth, that Reacheth them in Heaven. They know when any thing they have do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e on Earth is Blessed for others good, and Gods glory by two things, the <hi>Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation</hi> of their own Glory, and the <hi>Acclamation</hi> of Angels. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.20. speaks for this.</p>
               <p>Verily it is not then in vain to serve God; <hi>Godliness is great gain,</hi> its the most profitable, yea present gain, the most cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditable,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:204795:65"/> and prudentiall gain, in the whole world; O who would not glorify God? who is it that would not have plentifull Crops of Comfort, A whole Harvest of Happyness, Incomes of Glory, not only <hi>going with him</hi> at his Death, but continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>comeing after him</hi> in Glory?</p>
               <p>There is a three fold benefit of Gospel good works.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Unto them that do them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To those they are done for.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To them that see them done (but this may Especialy relate to works of Charity either to the Bodys or Souls of others.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> do again Exhort you to Glorify God, for you shall certainly in a very little time not only come to the Gates of Death, but also pass through them up to Gods great Tribunal to give an answer to this one Question, <hi>What have you all this while done for me?</hi> when ever God comes, he comes to <hi>Reckon,</hi> and when ever you go, you go to <hi>Reckon</hi> with him, how your time, strength, Parts, Estate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have been Improved; And let me tell you in the Name of God,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:204795:66"/> that it's not worth your while to live here, if it were not to Glorifie God. And let me tell you also, that if you do not, you take the ready way to shame your selves; (and that's a thing none loves) when you look back at last on the many years you have Rubbed through in the world, and think that of all that time, you never lived one day. For he that lives not to God, but lives in pleasure, <hi>is dead whilst he lives.</hi> Oh! how will these thieves that have Robbed God all their dayes be ashamed when catched at last by Death! Jer. 2.26. But the Apostle living for God, and lifting up the name of God, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that he should not be ashamed, Phil. 1.20, 21. <hi>According to my earnest expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that in nothing I shall be ashamed, &amp;c. For to me to live is Christ, and to dye is Gain.</hi> And take notice for your encouragement, to propose the glory of God as your utmost end, this is a way to put a beauty and lustre upon your meanest Services, to make all acceptable to God through Christ.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So much for the Motives.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:204795:66"/>
               <p>I shall now give you a few helps or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections how to glorifie God.</p>
               <p>It should be the language of all, how shall I come to glorifie God?</p>
               <p>I might show you how to do it in your hearts, in your Lips, and in your Lives distinctly: But.</p>
               <p>I shall only give you a few general helps, and put them all together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="direction">
               <head>Direction I.</head>
               <p>Get a Renewed Mind. Get into a State of Grace, else you can never glorifie God. The Apostle often makes this his Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to, and his supplication for, those he wrote unto.</p>
               <p>If you have the old carnal heart still, all other means will be ineffectual. You should Eye the glory of God in all you do: but how can you do this with no Eye, or a blind Eye? The Renewed Mind is the eye of the Soul, <hi>and if the Eye be dark, how great is the Darkness?</hi> You may seem to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:204795:67"/> Pray, Hear, and meditate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but you can never glorifie God without a new heart. Heb. 11.6. Rom. 8.7, 8. <hi>They that are in the Flesh cannot please God,</hi> that is, <hi>glorifie</hi> God. The Apostle when he Exhorts to prove the acceptable will of God, advises to this, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <hi>The Renewing of the mind:</hi> so <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.23. <hi>And they are happy, whose Inward Man is Renewed Day, by Day, though their outward man decay.</hi> Give God no rest till he give it you, Psal. 51.10. And be sure to Eye the Holy Ghost, to Renew the Spirit of your mind, that is, the Soul of your Soul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or the most inward part of your Soul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Renewing work is the work of the Holy Ghost, Tit. 3.5. and when you are <hi>Renewed;</hi> be much in waiting on God, Isa 40. last. Such shall <hi>Renew their Strength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a <hi>specifical Renovation</hi> in first Conversion, and a <hi>gradual Renovation</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. And both these are the work of the Holy Ghost; let Sinners pray for the one, and Saints for the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="direction">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:204795:67"/>
               <head>Direction II.</head>
               <p>Having got into a State of Grace, keep up the Lively Exercise of Grace daily. Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially some graces, without the Exercise of which God connot be actually glorified; while they are only in a dull sleepy habit, <hi>they</hi> do not so glorifie God. And these are especially.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Faith in the blood of Christ. Every day make it your work to believe as for your lives. Be much in Resting, and Rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon the Righteousness of another, you should not only fill your days with <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> but every <hi>Duty</hi> with <hi>grace,</hi> and this of all graces glorifies God, and he honours it. You ought not only to mind your being Justified and saved at last by Faith, but you should every day live by it. God is only glorified in and through Christ, and that especially by the Exercise of Faith. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham gave glory unto God by believing.</hi> Faith honours God by taking his bare naked word and Resting on it, <hi>and on him that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver saw.</hi> Our Divines have said, That a
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:204795:68"/> man glorifies God more by believing, than if he had never sinned, but perfectly obey-the Law. But it is certain, Faith makes a man <hi>Righteous</hi> in Gods account as though he had not sinned, which no other grace doth. Repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> does not make a man <hi>Righteous,</hi> but Faith doth. Christ (as you have heard under the Motives) glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified God, and he was eminent for Faith, he was the greatest Believer in the world, for he not only believed for himself, but his whole mysticall Body, <hi>his Faith was strong, Isa.</hi> 50.7, 9. <hi>Psal.</hi> 16.1. The grace of Faith glorifies all Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Attributes, his Son, Word, and Spirit, and it will correct sence and Reason. For when <hi>Sence</hi> saith such a thing <hi>will not be,</hi> and <hi>Reason</hi> saith it <hi>cannot be,</hi> saith <hi>Faith</hi> but it both <hi>Can, and will be,</hi> for God hath said it, it gives God its Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial, Joh. 3.23. It hath set to its Seal <hi>that God is true,</hi> and saith as <hi>Moses,</hi> when he must not go into <hi>Canaan,</hi> Deut. 32.4. <hi>he is a God of Truth and without iniquity, Just and Right is he,</hi> thus it honours God, and Justifies God, not imputing Sin to him, as he justifies the Soul, so Faith justifies him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:204795:68"/>2. You glorifie God by the lively Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of the grace of Love; and a Dormant Love doth not actually glorifie God. But Love will keep you doing, and will think nothing hard. Some things you may find more difficult than others, but Love covers many Infirmities, it suffers long, is not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily provoked, seeks not her own things, thinketh no evil, it will bear, believe, hope, and endure all things; hence the Angels that are all in a flame of Love to God, cry out, as Luke 2.14. <hi>Faith works by Love,</hi> its called the <hi>Labour of Love,</hi> Heb. 6.10. Love is of an opening nature, it expands and enlarges the heart towards God; hence it glorifies him, Psal. 24.7, 9. and it is of a constraining nature, 2 Cor. 5.14. A Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Adoption will make a man do more than all things else will, either shame, hell, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; if you let a Spirit of Adoption down, you can neither live usefully nor comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; hence the Saints in Heaven glorifie God perfectly, they Love him perfectly. Love <hi>counts none of Gods Commandments grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.3. This made <hi>David</hi> do so much, he loved much, as you find throughout the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:204795:69"/> 119. Psalm in many verses of it.</p>
               <p>So much as you Love, so much you glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God; if you Love not, you glorifie him not at all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Keep up the hopes of eternal glory, and this would help you to glorifie God, <hi>and despise all things below, and glory in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation</hi> &amp;c. Rom. 5.2, 3, 5. <hi>Its the love of God shed abroad in your hearts,</hi> will help you in all the Rest.</p>
               <p>See what was said in the former part of the Discourse, <hi>We must have much of Heav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in our Deportment,</hi> if we would glorifie God. That is, the hopes of heaven. This hope will purifie you, and so it glorifies God. It puts the Soul upon waiting quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, expecting earnestly, and preparing care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <hi>for the Coming of Christ,</hi> as persons do for a great Wedding. How should that Soul live <hi>to day</hi> that knows not but that it may live with God <hi>to morrow! You are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to this Hope,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. Hope is both of an Elevating, and endearing nature, and both these ways it glorifies God. The soul that has it, scorns the best of sublunary hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesses. And this Hope makes the Soul to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:204795:69"/> cleave to its object. Hope suits your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent condition, <hi>for it is an Anchor:</hi> nay, it gives you a sweet light in a night of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity. See how Hope glorifies God, Tit. 2.11, 12, 13. <hi>It will teach to deny all ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, and to live Soberly, Righteously and Godly, &amp;c.</hi> What will not your hopes of enjoying God for ever, make you do?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Keep up in fear, Keep down in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and keep on in Repentance and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sorrow, <hi>I</hi> put them all together. Take heed of making too bold with God, be humble, daily Repent and Confess your sins. You have heard already how <hi>these</hi> glorifie God, <hi>Isai.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Sanctifie the Lord in your hearts, and make him your fear and your Dread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if you would glorifie God, hate vain glory, and be much in denying your selves. <hi>Paul</hi> was an excellent Example in this, Phil. 3.4, 5. <hi>&amp;c. And God will have no flesh to glory before him,</hi> therefore he has said so much to prevent our glorying in any thing but God, and hath carried so in his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensations, 1 Cor. 1.26. to the 29. verse. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.2, 6, 7. if you will <hi>glory,</hi> do as
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:204795:70"/>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> did, 2 Cor. 12.9. <hi>Glory in your Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, that the power of Christ may Rest upon you:</hi> And Repent daily, for <hi>that</hi> gives God the glory which your sins took from him.</p>
               <trailer>So much for the Second Direction.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="direction">
               <head>Direction III.</head>
               <p>Labour to know God, and be mindful of him. These are of great use, for if you know not God, you cannot glorifie him: and though you do know him, if you forget him, you are like to do little at glorifying him, for actual Communion with God is not ordinarily without an act of the Memory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two Branches here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Labour to <hi>know God.</hi> This makes way <hi>for</hi> every thing that is <hi>good,</hi> by this you have right <hi>Notions of God,</hi> (as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the first Head in the Explication you may see) your Glorifying of God will be according to your knowledge o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:204795:70"/> him, sometimes God seems to hide himself, <hi>Job</hi> 23.3. O that I knew where I might find him! or it may be read, <hi>O that I knew how I might know him!</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For your help here take three Words of Advice;</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Beware of any idle, vain, or childish representations of God, or imaginations in your thoughts. These disshonour God as much as may be: never think of compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending him; for he is vastly, infinitely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove you. Take heed of imaginary, corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real, carnal shapes of God, cast them out with indignation, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.22. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Isai.</hi> 40.18. yet in that Chapter you have <hi>glorious Descriptions of God.</hi> Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are forbidden in the second Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that in our Heads as well as in Churches. Some Men have been so wicked as not only to picture God in their thoughts, but also in their Churches and Chambers, which is enough to make one tremble to think that they should go about to paint the infinite and everlasting <hi>Being.</hi> If it be
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:204795:71"/> hard and needless to picture an Angel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is a Spirit, how much more Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous is it to paint an increated Spirit, the Object of all Worship! But so bruitish have some been, that they have painted the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as an old Man, the Son as a young Man, or as a Lamb, and the Holy <hi>Ghost</hi> as a Dove; and the Trinity (in some <hi>Books</hi>) like the Sun with Beams, and the word <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah</hi> in the midst. These are idle and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable: for Christ himself (though a Man) cannot be pictured, it being hard to tell his features, and you must not please your fancies in it, and say as in other things <hi>so it pleased the Painter</hi> you would not like to have your own Picture so drawn. But if you could draw his bodily feature, yet you can't picture him fully, because of his two Natures. Though you have a Soul you may say men picture your Bodys, but still you have but one Nature.</p>
                  <p>And though God was pleased to appear in Shapes, yet what is that to the purpose. It was in Love and Mercy he thus Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended, and will you so abuse it? These things beget carnal thoughts of God, and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:204795:71"/> are so far from being profitable that it is an horrible abuse, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.22, 23, 24. And as these are unlawful, so <hi>carnal</hi> Representati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of him are very dishonouring to him. Yet often times gracious Souls may be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with these, and greatly perplexed from Satan, but if you hate them its matter of Comfort.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To such I would say that if indeed you hate them,</head>
                  <p n="1">1 God will not charge you with them, but lay them at Satans door, though its great cause of Humiliation to you to be capable of suffering such temptations, its a fruit of the Fall.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. You are not alone in this case, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gracious Souls have been thus afflicted, and many all their dayes subject to them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They will be but short, and if they last long they shall work for your good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>And for Direction to such I would say,</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Pray often to God about it, as a poor Prisoner at a Window, look out and call in Heaven against them, and God will Rate off Satan at last.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:204795:72"/>2. Resist them speedily, and don't think of them too much: the way to resist other Temptations is to study the evil of them, but these are to be thrown out im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, they are not to be disputed with.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Be diligently and spiritually imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, be not idle, that gives great advant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Keep reading the Promises, and avoid all needless <hi>solitude,</hi> be much in godly, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and lively Company.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If you would know God then study him much, and that in his properties, works, Word, Son, Spirit and Heaven.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This would help you to Know him and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Study Him in his Properties, look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him as your Catechism speaks, Infinite, Eternal, unchangeable, Incomprehensible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this is the way to apprehend his <hi>Being.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Study him in his Works: All the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> are his <hi>Preachers,</hi> they are his <hi>Library,</hi> and his <hi>Ladder:</hi> how wonderfully were
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:204795:72"/> all things made! <hi>Psal.</hi> 19.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. and as wonderfuly preserved and governed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from the <hi>Angel</hi> to the <hi>Worm:</hi> there are great mysterys in all. He works still <hi>John</hi> 5.17. that his <hi>Providence</hi> should so extend it self and that also both to good and evil, and yet <hi>pure</hi> notwithstanding is wonderful, and its both perfect, punctual and perpetual, if he should but take off his eye a moment, how would Sun, Moon and Stars drop? What a wonder is it that this <hi>Massey Earth</hi> should hang in the <hi>Air,</hi> when we cannot make a Feather to hang in it. Study these great Mysteries of Creation and Providence, and be before hand with Satan and your vain imaginations. Who is it that Thunders so marvelously, <hi>Psal.</hi> 29.3. &amp; 145.4. O all his Works praise him, and men should praise them, by and for them. You should do as they did, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.31. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.16. Look upon God as the <hi>Marrow,</hi> the <hi>Soul</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> the <hi>All</hi> of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Study God in his Word: Be well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Scriptures they Testifie of him. Glorious Descriptions you have of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:204795:73"/> him there, I mention none. Accustome your selves to think of him as set forth in his Word, this is more than in his works; here he is drawn to the life, his Characters much fuller and clearer: in his Works you may plainly guess there is a God, but here you may see what a God he is in part though you can never fully know him.</p>
                  <p>Here you have the Trinity set forth (which the Heathen never dreamed of, and the Quakers have sinned themselves into the unbelief of) and so that mystery of Gods being a Redeemer which could never be told by Natures light. How should you then prize the Scriptures! cleave close to them, and pity others that have them not, or that will not use them, their case is sad indeed, its a sign they never saw that Glory and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty that is in them.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Study God in his Son. The clearest, manifestation of God is in the Person of the Mediator, <hi>He</hi> hath <hi>Expounded</hi> him, <hi>Joh</hi> 1 18. (in the Greek) <hi>He is the Fathers Glass,</hi> Joh. 14.9. Heb. 1.3. Col. 1.15. in a clear Glass you may see every feature perfectly 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4, 6. <hi>He is the Image of God,</hi> so a
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:204795:73"/> Gods Glory shines in the face of Christ, he is Gods face; the most beautiful part of a Man is his Face. God who dwells in Light that none can approach to, 2 <hi>Tim▪</hi> 6.16▪ may be seen here in his glory, which otherwise we could not behold: as we may see the Sun in a dish of water, which else cannot be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at▪ Gods Glory especially in his wisdome, and goodness shines clearly in the Mediator, you may see Gods Majesty in himself, and yet his condescendency in Christ. O that lovely and useful Remedy that is appointed to heal our ignorance of God!</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Study God in his Spirit. He discovers himself in Christ by his Spirit. Study God in the new Creation as well as in the old in the works of Grace as well as in the works of Nature. O what a God must that be that makes a blind Soul to see! a dead Soul to live and breathe! See him in this, and Admire.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Study God in his Heaven. There he is most glorious. Suppose that (with <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi>) you saw the Heavens opened, and God there with that innumerable Company of glorious Saints and Angels about him, praise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:204795:74"/> and magnifying of him, and if you could hope to be one of them ere long, would it not raise your Spirit? He directs us to this in the Lords Prayer <hi>(Our Father which art in Heaven)</hi> as if he would have us at the beginning of every Service to wind up our hearts to Heaven, it denotes his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that he dwells in such a place. You count him poor that lives in a Cottage, so on the contrary, great, that lives in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If you would know God be often in those places where he most discovers himself in his Glory. There are not only some times, but some places also, where God es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially discovers himself; and you should not only study him, but wait on him in those places:</p>
                  <p>And they are two principally;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>In the Temple,</hi> be no strangers to Publick Ordinances, hearing the Word o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened and applyed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We are most fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar in our own Houses, so is God in his it is called, <hi>the place where his Honour dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth;
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:204795:74"/> He comes to his Temple, Mal.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Christ was found in the Temple Luke</hi> 2.46. <hi>He will feed there, Mic,</hi> 5.4. He is usually found there at first and afterwards, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. You should love the Word and desire it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the Closet, upon your Knees, O pray for this, that God would discover him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self unto you. Pray as he did, Exod. 33.18. and as Psal. 63.2 <hi>To see his Glory.</hi> O pray whatever you do. A <hi>Prayerless</hi> man is a <hi>godless, graceless</hi> man, (but this <hi>I</hi> have largely spoke to from other Texts.) And when you have thus prayed, be Tractable and Ready to receive his Impressions and Discoveries. Pray <hi>and Look up,</hi> Psal. 5.3. it will come by little and little; plead with God for it, and you have many arguments to plead.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That he has given you a Soul capable of knowing him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That he has Enlightned as blind and dark Souls as yours are.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That he has made a Covenant-promise of this, <hi>That he will give a heart to know him, and that they shall be all Taught of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:204795:75"/>4. And (if you can plead it) that you desire to <hi>know</hi> him, only that you might <hi>love and serve</hi> him. And he has said, <hi>you shall know if you thus follow on to know him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Second Branch.</p>
                  <p>Be mindful of Him, for if you forget him, you cannot glorifie him.</p>
                  <p>Let him be in your thoughts much, Psa. 16.8. <hi>I have set the Lord always before me.</hi> Luke 1.75. <hi>Before Him.</hi> Let your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge further your Remembrance of him. To forget him argues open Impiety, or secret Hypocrisie, <hi>Job.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Psal.</hi> 10.4. Some persons think of him after a bad man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and so dishonour him; and others do it by forgetting of him, as if God were not worthy to be thought on. And you are all prone to this Evil. Learn to <hi>send,</hi> to <hi>Bend,</hi> and to <hi>bind</hi> your <hi>Thoughts</hi> this way to abide with God.</p>
                  <p>Labour to know and think so much of God, as to prefer him, and Communion with him above all things, so as to set up an high Throne for him in your Souls, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:204795:75"/> nothing more than to glorifie him, and to be glorified with him, so as to say with him, <hi>Psal.</hi> 73.25. <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? &amp;c.</hi> It is a wonder we can forget him, for the Creation is full of him, which might put us in mind of him; his mercies are many, and are as so many <hi>Motives</hi> and <hi>Memorandums</hi> to us, and there is one <hi>Ordinance</hi> that is on purpose appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for this end that we might Remember. <hi>Do this in Remembrance of me:</hi> And though this sin of forgetting God be little noted, yet it is a Mother-sin, and sorely threatned, Psal. 9.17. <hi>The wicked shall be turned into Hell, and all the Nations that forget God. Psal.</hi> 50.22. <hi>Consider this all ye that forget God, lest God tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you.</hi> What a dreadful word is this?</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>So much for the Third Direction.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="direction">
               <head>Direction IV.</head>
               <p>Accustome your selves very much unto a Life of Praise, this is the way to glorifie
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:204795:76"/> God. This would fit you for Heaven; the first word you shall say There is <hi>Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah.</hi> It is <hi>Angels</hi> work, and <hi>Heavens</hi> work, be found much in it; and it would also help you against Unbelieving Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly, for there is Love, Gratitude, and Joy in it. It keeps off Satan, and keeps you near God, and though you may be at a loss about your interest in him, yet praise him for his Divine Properties, and bless him for his Christ, and what he hath done for you, though evet so little.</p>
               <p>And Read those Scriptures often that put you upon this duty, the Book of Psalms is full to this purpose. And this is most suitable for a <hi>Lords Day</hi> especially. We have all something to bless him for, either what we <hi>have had,</hi> what we <hi>have,</hi> or what we <hi>hope to have.</hi> But if you have nothing else to bless him for, bless him that you are <hi>out of Hell,</hi> and under the <hi>Call</hi> of the Gospel. <hi>Praises</hi> ought to have their due share in all our <hi>Prayers;</hi> but alas, how often are they shut out, and all our time filled with Complaints! we either forget to praise, or are short and perfunctory in
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:204795:76"/> it. Christ did not teach us so to do, for the Lords Prayer begins and ends with praise.</p>
               <p>If you can't bless him for some bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, <hi>as saving grace, &amp;c.</hi> yet you might praise him for his <hi>own Excellencies. I</hi> say as Psal. 107.8.15. &amp;c. <hi>O that men would praise the Lord, for his Goodness, and for his wonderful works to the Children of Men.</hi> This would set off God and his ways in the world. And if you would accustome your selves to it, it would make it become easy to you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="direction">
               <head>Direction V.</head>
               <p>Keep your Eye upon the whole Compass and Circumference of your Duty, and see that all be done as God expects it from you.</p>
               <p>Much is to be done if you would glorifie God. Look not at it with a squint Eye, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience doth much glorifie God, but do not pick and choose your Duty, you must be universal in your Obedience, or else you will be ashamed, Psal. 119.6. There must be no sin loved, no Duty neglected. And
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:204795:77"/>
                  <hi>the Commandment is exceeding broad, Psal.</hi> 119.96. When an Instrument hath many strings, it requires the more skill in manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. You are to mind both Law and Gospel. The Moral Law is a <hi>Rule</hi> though not a <hi>Covenant</hi> to Believers, (do not think that Christ who was made a <hi>Curse</hi> for fin, will be a <hi>Cloak</hi> for it,) and this Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns heart sins, and sins of Omission, <hi>&amp;c. You are to hate every false way, and in all things to live honestly; to have a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science both towards God, all men, and your selves, &amp;c.</hi> You must see to <hi>Faith in Christ, and Repentance towards God.</hi> You are to mind the Duties of both Tables, and to see that there be <hi>Faith</hi> in all you do towards God, and towards men <hi>Charity, Justice, meekness;</hi> and as to your selves <hi>Sobriety, and Self-denial.</hi> Take heed of minding one duty so, as to neglect another. In general see to an humble, heavenly, blameless Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation; that so others may glorifie God for you. Nothing like <hi>practical Godliness,</hi> 2 Thes. 1.11, 12. Let God be glorified by your <hi>walking worthy of your Calling.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneness dishonours him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. Some
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:204795:77"/> Professors carry as if they had nothing to do <hi>for God</hi> in the world, others carry as if they came from Hell <hi>to do the Devils work,</hi> and to glorifie Satan, and many walk as if they carried Christ up and down in the world only to <hi>Reproach</hi> him, this is woful. But mind you your whole Duty, and leave not out those Duties especially, that even some wicked men have skill in, as Justice, Temperance, Mercy, Charity, Meekness, <hi>&amp;c. But be you spiritual in all</hi> this is to be like God and Christ, Eph. 5, 1, 2. <hi>To be Imitators of Christ, as he imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Father, John</hi> 5.19. Imitation eve-discovers high Estimation. Compare Mat. 5. ult. with Luke 6.36. Carry <hi>witnessingly, Convincingly, Tit.</hi> 2.10. 1 Pet. 3.1. 1 Pet. 2.12. <hi>In the day of Visitation</hi> that they may be forced to glorifie God, <hi>q. d. When he shall visit them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mind <hi>Comliness</hi> in all you do, and what is of <hi>good Report,</hi> as well as what is <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi> And be always doing something more than others, that is <hi>harder</hi> and more <hi>hidden</hi> Duties than what others do. And do not do that your selves, which you forbid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:204795:78"/> to do. The Scripture is full as to all these things, but <hi>I</hi> forbear any more.</p>
               <p>Mind also in your doing, both the <hi>manner</hi> after which you are to do all, and that you act from right ends, and from right princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and provoked to it by Gospel Motives, and that you do all <hi>orderly,</hi> the greatest Duty in the first place, and <hi>seasonably;</hi> for if you be cutting with your Ax when you should be smoothing with your plain, you will make but a bad piece of work of it. God complains of some, that he found not their works <hi>perfect,</hi> they should be perfect in all their <hi>parts,</hi> though they cannot be so as to their <hi>degree,</hi> the want of any of these, is as an hair in your pen, that blots all. When God bids you serve him, he bids you to do it fervently; zeal and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance should go together. You must not only <hi>hear,</hi> but you must be <hi>swift to hear;</hi> not only give to the poor, but <hi>draw out your Soul,</hi> as well as your Mony. Thus you are to mind the manner of all you do. If you wind up a Watch, and do not set the finger right, it will go wrong. If the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row be drawn up to the head, and directed
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:204795:78"/> to a wrong Mark, the Game is lost: and a Man may loose by shooting short, or over, as well as by shooting wide.</p>
               <p>You are to do all, not only <hi>in Faith,</hi> and in the Name of Christ, but <hi>in fear,</hi> also or else it cannot be acceptable, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. you must do all by <hi>Rule,</hi> Gal. 6.16 bring all your work to the Rule. If the Mariner mind not every point of the Compass he will make sad work: you should Trade by <hi>Rule,</hi> Pray, Hear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do all <hi>by Rule.</hi> These things have been so plainly and plentifully opened on other Subjects, that I say no more of them here.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="direction">
               <head>Direction VI.</head>
               <p>Get and keep your selves in some measure fit for <hi>suffering.</hi> Get such Graces as will fit you <hi>for,</hi> and Adorn you <hi>in</hi> your <hi>Suffering.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may <hi>be near it,</hi> for ought I know▪ be <hi>fit for it,</hi> that God may be glorified by you, as (no doubt) he is by a holy, humble suffering for him. Get much Faith, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Zeal, Boldness for God; O how was God glorified by the Martyrs of old! and so
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:204795:79"/> also by the death of Christ; so that they that stood by cried out, <hi>This is the Son of God,</hi> John 21.19. <hi>Isai.</hi> 24.15. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14. The <hi>Spirit of Glory</hi> is more than <hi>the Spirit of Grace,</hi> and that shall <hi>rest</hi> upon you. When you suffer you should be concerned for Gods Glory, as Christ was, <hi>John</hi> 17.1. you do not know but God may call for that which is Dearest to you: O be like Christ, that in every thing denied himself, vailing his own glory, though he did not quit it; for (as one well saith) all the Honour pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible is due to the Humane Nature of Christ, from the very first moment of of its being united to the person of the Son of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. and yet all this he willingly laid aside to glorifie God in the work of Redemption, living like <hi>a Servant,</hi> and dying like a <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And (to Comfort you) this is the way to <hi>Glory, Luke</hi> 24.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>if we suffer with him, we shall be glorified with him, Rom.</hi> 10.10. <hi>With the mouth Confession is made unto Salvation, Gal</hi> 6.17. <hi>He went to his Slaughtering-House as to a Wedding-house,</hi> John 14. ult <hi>Arise, let us go hence;</hi>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:204795:79"/> so should you suffer with <hi>Chearfulness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if you should not be called to suffer <hi>Death,</hi> yet if to suffer <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Reproach</hi> for Christ, you should <hi>Rejoice.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles did thus: and <hi>Triumphed</hi> in Christ Jesus, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. to Sing in the <hi>Stocks,</hi> and embrace <hi>Faggots,</hi> is highly Glorifying and pleasing to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="direction">
               <head>Direction VII.</head>
               <p>Make it your great buisness to Glorify Jesus Christ the Son of God: if you would glorify God, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 4.11. he is glorifyed (as you heard before) <hi>through Christ.</hi> When you glorify Christ you honour God, for <hi>He</hi> seeks <hi>his</hi> glory all along; hence has he suffered the <hi>worst of evils</hi> to be in them that he intends to save by Christ, that he may let us see he <hi>Loves</hi> Christ more, than he <hi>hates</hi> Sinners. (But this is no Encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement to sin.) That must needs be on Excellent Bloud that takes away such staines: nay (as some of our <hi>Divines</hi> have said) <hi>God Suffered</hi> Adam <hi>to fall, that so Christ might have the Honour of Raising up fallen man again.</hi> And the Ministry is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to honour Christ; the Spirit in
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:204795:80"/> the Preaching of the Gospel takes of <hi>Christs</hi> and showes it unto us, <hi>John</hi> 16.14▪ hence (as some observe out of <hi>John</hi> 17.10.) when Christ prayed before for himself, he used that Argument <hi>that he had Glorifyed God;</hi> now he prays for his Disciples, his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, <hi>that they had Glorified him,</hi> to signify that this was well pleasing to God.</p>
               <p>And you Glorify Christ by seeing your need of him; and when you come unto him by Faith, and Close with him, when you depend on him, and profess him, and walk-seriously before him, and suffer for him when called to it <hi>(as before)</hi> when you Bless God for Christ, and wholly Live to him, and account <hi>all things Dross in Comparison of him;</hi> when he is much in your <hi>Head, Heart, Mouth,</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> when you walk as his Members, and trust in his <hi>Righteousness,</hi> and though the <hi>Papists</hi> have Reproched it, yet you will find it will not deceive you at Death. Where pure Righteousness <hi>Leads</hi> the <hi>Van,</hi> Glory comes in the <hi>Rear Isai.</hi> 58.8. Christs Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eousness is your glory, Oh Glorify God by puting it on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="direction">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:204795:80"/>
               <head>Direction VIII. And Lastly.</head>
               <p>Get and Keep to high and noble Ends in all you do.</p>
               <p>This Glorifying God is in it self <hi>a Noble Work, an high Raised Work,</hi> and can never be <hi>Sincerely, Evenly,</hi> and <hi>Ʋniversally</hi> Managed with <hi>Low Ends.</hi> If your <hi>Ends</hi> be <hi>Low</hi> your <hi>Lives</hi> can never be <hi>High.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Its a pitty that <hi>Heaven-born</hi> Souls should mind <hi>mean</hi> things. O be where your head the Lord Jesus Christ is, <hi>Col▪</hi> 3.1, 2 we see it Daily and every where, that the End (let it be wherever it will) is of a <hi>Drawing, Directing,</hi> and <hi>Overcomeing</hi> Nature.</p>
               <p>This makes Sinners to be as they are, their carnal Ends in all things govern them. Hence its impossible to make a Sinner for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake his way till he hath new ends given him by heart-changing Grace. Now as the divine Glory is, or ought to be, every mans great end (as in the Text) so there are some other noble ends that would fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this great end if they were daily kept up in the <hi>Conscience, Power, pleasure and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>In Particular <hi>these six Ends,</hi> with which <hi>I</hi> shall Conclude.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:204795:81"/>1. <hi>Aim now at perfect Mortification and Holiness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Its true <hi>that you cannot attain it</hi> must be taken for granted; yet its your Duty to <hi>Aim at it,</hi> its the very nature of the new nature so to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>True Grace</hi> is not contented with <hi>Little Grace.</hi> Herein lies Gospel Perfection.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In giving all it hath to God in the Name of Christ. God has that from the Soul that no creature in the World hath, and he can do that for God every day, that he would nevet do for any other. And that's not all, but</p>
               <p n="2">2. When it hath done all this, its hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grieved that it can do no more. And also,</p>
               <p n="3">3. It keeps on <hi>Mortifying Sin,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting Holiness</hi> (in order unto glorifying God) without setting any bounds or limits to it self. And in this it out-does the most flourishing Hypocrite in the World) a good Soul would (if it could) be infinitely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged in love to God, and hatred to sin.</p>
               <p>It is your Duty to <hi>Aim at the perfect Mortification of your Sins, and perfect Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi> And that not only (thô mainly)
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:204795:81"/> because the holy and spotless Law of God requires it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Cursed is every one that continueth not in all things that are written in the Law to do them,</hi> Mat. 5. last. <hi>Be ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as your Father which is in Heaven is perfect.</hi> And you are commanded to love the Lord your God, <hi>with all your heart, mind soul and strength,</hi> &amp;c. And Christ teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you to pray that you may not be <hi>lead into Temptation, but delivered from all Evil,</hi> Mat 6.13. and the Apostle prayes for his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7▪ <hi>I pray God that) ye do no Evil:</hi> and 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 5.23. Yea (as one well saith) even pardoned Persons themselves, are strictly bound unto the Law for Duty as well as Adam, though not with such evil Consequences; they may be in danger of contracting Sin, though not in danger of incurring Death by the breach of it. And the Law is as much a <hi>Rule</hi> to them as ever, though no more a <hi>Covenant,</hi> and though Believers are delivered from the <hi>Curse</hi> of the Law, yet not from the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding</hi> power of it. Our being set at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from the curse of the Law, does not discharge us from the Duty and Obedience we owe unto it. The Law of God being
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:204795:82"/> as just and full of equity as ever, though we have unhappily lost our power to keep it, and Christ <hi>came not to destroy the Law but to fulfil it.</hi> And when he justifies any person, he does not give him a liberty to sin, or disoblige him from Duty; so that still the Law is in force as a Rule to the end of the World, and requires perfect Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and perfect holiness and conformity to God, therefore you should <hi>Aim at it.</hi> (Tho' God is pleased through the Merits and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness of Christ to pardon Imperfections, when the heart sincerely Aims at and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs perfection) and not only should the Command of the Law put you upon thus Aiming at perfection, but there are two special advantages would he the Consequence of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It would be a comfortable evidence of your Uprightness: and an <hi>Ʋpright Man</hi> God accounts a <hi>perfect Man,</hi> Gen. 17.1. <hi>Walk thou before me, and be thou perfect,</hi> (in the Margent) <hi>be thou sincere:</hi> Psal: 18.23. <hi>I was also upright before him, and I kept my self from</hi> mine <hi>Iniquity.</hi> If any sin be indulged, or Duty neglected, you cannot have good evidence of your sincerity. And this aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:204795:82"/> at perfection, both in Mortification and Holiness, would argue the truth both of your Love and Hatred. When you take your Aim, by 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. having therefore these pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promises, <hi>let us cleanse our selves from all filthiness of Flesh &amp; Spirit,</hi> (there is Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <hi>perfecting holiness,</hi> (there is vivification.)</p>
               <p>You are not only to cleanse your selves from <hi>sins of the Flesh,</hi> that are of a grosser nature, but <hi>Sins of the Spirit, all Spiritual Filthiness; Spiritual Pride, Heart-Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,</hi> &amp;c. Nay, <hi>all Filthiness,</hi> so that the Evil One may not so much as <hi>Touch</hi> you. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.18. and to keep <hi>Ʋnspotted of the World,</hi> Jam. 1.27. <hi>Some things are not to be named by you, Eph.</hi> 5.3. And this is not all, but afterwards you must go on, <hi>perfecting Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in the Fear of God;</hi> and all this from a most Gospel Motive, <hi>viz</hi> the <hi>Covenant-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises</hi> that are mentioned in the end of the foregoing Chapter</p>
               <p>Thus if you would have an Evidence of your sincerity, you must design perfection.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It would also be a notable help to your <hi>proficiency</hi> in the ways of God; and your <hi>great Attainments</hi> would greatly glorifie God. He that shoots at the Moon
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:204795:83"/> shoots higher than he that shoots at a Mole Hill. Though you cannot reach Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet you would by thus Aiming at it, Reach further than those who only set themselves such, or such a measure of Grace.</p>
               <p>O therefore if you would glorifie God greatly, get great measures of grace; let your Ends and Aims be great; no less than perfection in grace. Do as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.11, 12, 13, 14, 15. Aim at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of the Dead, at <hi>a sinless Estate; Forgetting those things that are behind;</hi> be earnestly <hi>pressing forward,</hi> and <hi>Reaching forth</hi> (as a man Running a Race stretches forth his Body, and makes towards the Mark, so do you) <hi>toward the Mark for the Prize,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Metaphor drawn from the <hi>Olympick</hi> Games, where many Run, but one Obtained the Prize. <hi>If by any means I might attain to the Resurrection of the Dead.</hi> See how earnest the Apostle was in this matter, and he makes it his <hi>one Thing</hi> he had to do.</p>
               <p>And these designs would further you greatly in your Glorifying God.</p>
               <p>So much for the first thing you should Aim at.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:204795:83"/>2. <hi>Aim at frequent sensible Communion with God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I shall be short in this, and the Rest, for the first was <hi>that I</hi> chiefly intended. But Aim at this, it is an high and Noble End; and design the Enjoyment of God in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ordinance, and upon all occasions. This would help you to glorifie God, for then you might expect to enjoy him. Let your Souls follow hard after God. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be sure to give Christ his due place, and honour, in all your making out after Comunion with God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18. <hi>He</hi> seems to bespeak it, John 14.6. <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life; no man cometh unto the Father but by me.</hi> Therefore be sure to mind Christ in all you do.</p>
               <p>And it would be good every Evening for you to observe what Transactions, and out-goings have passed between you and the blessed God. On Gods part, what of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers of grace, what Quicknings and Breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his Spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And on your part, what openings unto God, what Receivings from him, what meltings of Soul, and humblings before him, and what Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of his Presence and Providences, you have made, and what out-goings, and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:204795:84"/> earnest Breathings of Soul, to God, have passed from you: and accordingly you are to carry in a way either of Humiliation or Thanksgiving. Whilst some are saying, <hi>Who will shew us any good?</hi> Say you with <hi>David, Lord lift thou up the Light of thy Countenance upon us. Psal.</hi> 4.6, 7. While others have their <hi>Portion in this Life,</hi> and have their Bellies filled with Gods Hid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure (both at Sea and Land) Let it be your great Ambition to <hi>Behold Gods Face in Righteousness, and to be satisfied with his Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness Psal.</hi> 17. <hi>ult.</hi> And though you may not know what Raptures and Ravishing Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Enlargements mean, yet see to walk humbly with God, and Aim at daily, Soul Transforming, and Endearing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him.</p>
               <p>And hereby you will be holpen to this great Duty of glorifying God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Aim at Ʋniversal Edification.</hi> Let every body be the better for you. Let this be the design of your Soul, although too often you may fall short of what you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign. <hi>Let all things be done to Edifying,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.26. There is an ungodly Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you read of, 1 Cor. 8.10. <hi>Emboldened,</hi> it is in the Greek <hi>Edifyed,</hi> when we by
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:204795:84"/> our Example make others bold to sin, beware of this, let your Carriage be such as may Edify Beholders. And your <hi>Speech always with Grace seasoned with Salt, that you may know how you ought to answer every man,</hi> Col. 4.6. <hi>Let no Corrupt Communication come out of your mouth, but that which is good to the use of Edifying, that it may Minister Grace to the Hearers.</hi> Eph. 4.29. Especially when you mention the great Name of God, do it Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently, and Admiringly, Take heed of speaking <hi>lightly</hi> of good things. It is to be bewailed, that many times the good Discourse of some is so weakly managed, that it rather makes sport to others, and sets them a Laughing, then Convinces and Edifies them. May you not have as much Reason to speak Admiringly and Reverently as <hi>David?</hi> and how does he Abound this way, the 145 <hi>Psalm</hi> most of it is spent this way▪ but in the 5th <hi>&amp;</hi> 6th verses, he would so speak of God as to set others a speaking so too. And may not you say with him, as <hi>Psal.</hi> 35.10. <hi>All my bones shall say, who is a God like unto thee?</hi> so all my Sins, my Soul, my Wants, may you say, speak thus. Your savoury, holy and reverent speeches would greatly edifie others and glorifie God.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:204795:85"/>
               <p>And unto all that has been said <hi>I</hi> would give you this Advice, <hi>Wherein you fall short in one thing, Labour to abound in another Duty, that you may have more skill in, and Ability for.</hi> It is true you are to do your best in all; yet if you unwillingly fall short in Active Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Labour to make it up in your Passive Obedience (if called to it) if you fall short in <hi>Action,</hi> be sure to make it up in <hi>Affection,</hi> (But beware of deceiving your selves here) and what you cannot do your selves, as Acts of Charity <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Labour the more to stir up others to do it, what ever good it be, and God will set it to your Account as done by you for his Glory.</p>
               <p>And your high and Lofty Aimes in all this would mightily further your Glorifying of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Aim now in every thing you do, at a most Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable going off the Stage of this World.</hi> O Aim at this, and live like them that Aim at glorifying God by their death, in passing Honourably and Gloriously through it.</p>
               <p>Be every day taking the most likely way to aveit thus. Keep Conscience so now in peace &amp; power, that this may readily be effected at last. And though you may dye in the dark, as many a good Soul hath <hi>(for as grace is free, so Comfort also)</hi> yet now Aim at, and labour for an <hi>Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Entrance into the Eternal Kingdom,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11 There is a great deal of difference in Ships com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Harbour, some come with their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors lost, Sails torn, and Mast gone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:204795:85"/> they come in with all their Sails and Flag up: O be often Aiming to come <hi>gallantly</hi> into the Harbour of Glory. And you should be in such a Frame as to long for the day (but alas, few need Mr. <hi>Dods</hi> Advice to be patient to stay <hi>till God sent for them,</hi>) and be willing to wait his Time; very few in our days are so fond of going to Heaven, as to be in such haste; but Aim you at it, and at a <hi>Tall Stature</hi> in Christ. O labour to find, &amp; feel your selves daily fitting for that sinless Estate before you, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12. <hi>to find your selves made meet for the Inheritance of the Saints in Light:</hi> And that God is daily working of you up, framing and fashioning of you, for that self-fame thing, 2 Cor. 5.5. <hi>He that hath wrought us for the self-same thing is God, &amp;c.</hi> Let your <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> not your <hi>sins</hi> follow you into another world, Rev. 14.13 but O the miserable case of such, <hi>whose works follow them</hi> in a bad senee, all their sins, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>desert of</hi> them, but not the <hi>pleasure</hi> of them, and though they would gladly have them stay behind, <hi>(for they are said to lye down with them in their Graves) Job</hi> 20.11. yet they will not, but follow them to the Judgment-seat, and down to Hell again, there <hi>to be their Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi> On the other hand what a Comfortable thing it is when your Prayers, Tears, Alms, Faith, Repentance, Self-denyal, Patience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Follow you. And this is it you should in all you do be aiming at, for this you have a promise Psal. 126▪ ult▪ <hi>They that sow in Tears shall Reap in
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:204795:86"/> Joy, he that goeth forth weeping bearing precious seed shall doubtless come again with Rejoycing, bringing his Sheaves with him;</hi> they shall have Sheaves of Comfort and Glory then, for all their Toil and Tears now. O be often taking a fair farewel of all this world, at least aiming at thus doing.</p>
               <p>And for your great encouragement take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of this, that none of the Actings of your grace, shall ever be lost, as you see in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Text, there is an Harvest of Joy after a seed-time of grace. And the Reason is <hi>God observes all, and Books all;</hi> and though your grace may lie in a little room, so that it may well be compared to a grain of Mustard-seed, the least of all Seeds, yet it shall not be lost, and though none in the world has been able to see many of the Actings of your grace, yet you may say as she did in another case, Gen. 16.3. <hi>Thou God seest me!</hi> he is graciously <hi>by you,</hi> and sees your secret Closings with Christ, your Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Meltings, Heart-breaking, Relentings of Soul, not a sigh but he takes notice of it, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Groan or moan but he hears it, not one act of grace but it is all naked and bare to him; and he takes himself as glorified by all these, as you have heard; and then will surely Reward them with glory in another world; and if so, then the comfortable Reflection, upon all these must needs help to make your going off the Stage very <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and Comfortable.</hi> O then abound in these and that's the way; daily be designing this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:204795:86"/> End. So much for the fourth noble end we are to Aim at daily, <hi>that so we may eminently Glorify God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Aim daily to have a pleasant smiling Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance at the Morning of the Resurrection.</hi> Aim at nothing short of exceeding joy then in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day, <hi>and to be without spot or fault,</hi> Jude 24. Aim now to have a <hi>Crown there,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.8. Let your happiness lye in the Second Coming of Christ; <hi>be looking at the Recompence in the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Luke</hi> 14.14 And that's the last time to take <hi>Mony</hi> in: Let it be <hi>your</hi> great care and <hi>Study</hi> then to have <hi>your</hi> Account <hi>weighty</hi> in a good sence, and (as was said in the last particular) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound much in the Exercise of Grace, and if <hi>you Go</hi> off the Stage well <hi>at Death,</hi> You will fare well <hi>here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And O what a Day will that be when all the Saints shall Lift up their heads before God, and Angels, while all others shall find their Faces gathering <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Blackness!</hi> when the <hi>Arch Angel</hi> shall sound and gather all his Armies together, O what a <hi>Day of Congregation</hi> will it be! and what a sad Day will it be to some, that must find it a <hi>Day of Separation;</hi> and that for ever! But to the Saints a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Day</hi> and <hi>Glorious,</hi> when Each of them shall <hi>Shine as the Sun in the greatest Splendour,</hi> and more. <hi>O how will the Vaults of Heaven Ring with their joyfull Acclamations! O what a Train will follow the Captain of your Solvation!</hi> and what a <hi>Shout</hi> will they give, when they
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:204795:87"/> take Leave of a <hi>Reprobate World.</hi> And if you would Look with a <hi>Pleasant face then,</hi> Aime at, Designe for it <hi>now:</hi> Glorify God much, that's the way to it; and often Renewing your <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes,</hi> for this would also fit you to Glorify God.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Aime at the highest Degrees of Glory in another World.</hi> There are Degrees of Glory is plain, and many Arguments might prove it, Oh! <hi>Aime at the highest Degrees of it,</hi> if you would Glorify God here under the Influence of these high and noble ends, and amongst the rest Aime at <hi>Heaven,</hi> at nothing short of <hi>Heaven,</hi> Oh! <hi>Seek for Glory, Honour, and Immortallity.</hi> Rom. 2.7. And the greatest Degrees of it: Count it not enough to have only so much Religion as will keep Life, and Soul together, that will <hi>only</hi> bear <hi>your</hi> Charges to Heaven, but be <hi>Ambitious</hi> of being great in Heavens Court, and <hi>Intimate favourites of the Most High.</hi> Let us be persons of great <hi>Aims</hi> and <hi>Designs;</hi> and this is one especial <hi>way of Glorifying God. AMEN.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus you have in these few and plain Discourses seen that it is your great Duty to</hi> Glorifie God; <hi>and had some help afforded you for the doing of it. If</hi> God may be Glorified, you Converted, Edified <hi>or</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted <hi>I should Rejoyce; and if it should be otherwise, my Soul desires to weep in secret for your Pride and Misery.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>